<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Abbington House Rehab</title>
	<atom:link href="https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 15:25:42 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-GB</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.8.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/cropped-abbington-favicon-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Abbington House Rehab</title>
	<link>https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>How to Find the Best Rehab in the UK (What to Look For in 2025)</title>
		<link>https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/rehab-advice/best-rehab-uk/</link>
					<comments>https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/rehab-advice/best-rehab-uk/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ellyn Iacovou]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 15:13:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Rehab Advice]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/?p=49102</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[There is no such thing as the "best rehab in the UK" - only one that fits your unique needs and requirements. This guide will show you what to look for. ]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>When you’re searching for the best rehab in the UK, you’re not just comparing facilities &#8211; you’re making one of the most personal, emotional and potentially life-saving decisions of your life or someone else’s. And yet, in a digital landscape crowded with promises, “top 10” lists, and sales funnels, knowing who to trust can feel impossible.</p>



<p>The truth? There’s <strong>no single rehab that’s right for everyone</strong>. What matters isn’t who ranks #1 on a search results page &#8211; it’s whether a place offers the kind of safety, support, and personalised care you or your loved one genuinely need.</p>



<p>As someone who has worked with a number of treatment providers in the UK, I can honestly say that there is a rehab that is right for everyone. However, one point I would really like to drive home here is this: <strong>paying more for rehab does not equate to better recovery success rates</strong>. </p>



<p>In this guide,  we’ll show you <strong>how to tell the difference between surface-level marketing and true, evidence-based treatment environments</strong> — so that you can decide what “best” really means for you.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">What Does “Best Rehab” Actually Mean?</h3>



<p>If you type &#8220;best rehab UK&#8221; into Google, you&#8217;ll find dozens of articles claiming to rank the top centres. But if you dig a little deeper, you&#8217;ll notice something troubling: many of these lists aren&#8217;t based on clinical quality, outcomes, or ethics. </p>



<p>This isn’t just misleading, it can be dangerous. Addiction is a serious health issue, and the decision to enter rehab deserves better than sales tactics.</p>



<p>So let’s step back and ask: What does “best” actually mean?</p>



<p>At its core, the best rehab for you is one that:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Offers <strong>genuinely personalised, evidence-based care</strong></li>



<li>Provides <strong>a safe, supportive environment</strong> for detox and recovery</li>



<li>Understands and treats <strong>underlying causes</strong> like trauma or mental health issues</li>



<li>Supports <strong>long-term wellbeing</strong>, not just short-term abstinence</li>



<li>Prioritises <strong>your dignity, autonomy, and emotional safety</strong></li>
</ul>



<p>Everything else &#8211;  the views, the price tag, the luxury &#8211; comes second to the actual quality of care.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="940" height="730" src="https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/about-1.webp" alt="" class="wp-image-41575" srcset="https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/about-1.webp 940w, https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/about-1-300x233.webp 300w, https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/about-1-768x596.webp 768w, https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/about-1-386x300.webp 386w, https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/about-1-30x23.webp 30w, https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/about-1-13x10.webp 13w" sizes="(max-width: 940px) 100vw, 940px"></figure>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">7 Signs of a Truly High-Quality Rehab</h3>



<p>A beautiful website doesn’t mean a rehab is safe or effective. If you want to cut through the noise, these are the markers to look for &#8211; the features that truly define a centre as among the “best.”</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">1. Medically Supervised Detox On-Site</h4>



<p>Alcohol and drug withdrawal can be painful, distressing, and even life-threatening. A top-tier rehab doesn’t just offer emotional support &#8211; it includes<strong> medical care</strong> for people going through detox.</p>



<p>Look for:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Medical specialists, including doctors or nursing professionals</li>



<li>On-site prescribing for detox medications (like Librium or Subutex)</li>



<li>Clear protocols for managing withdrawal symptoms</li>



<li>A warm, monitored environment &#8211; not a clinical ward</li>
</ul>



<p>Without this, you risk either being referred elsewhere for detox or being left to manage dangerous symptoms alone.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">2. Personalised, Individual Therapy</h4>



<p>One of the most common traps in lower-tier rehab centres is the overuse of group therapy. While peer support is valuable, it should never <strong>replace</strong> dedicated one-to-one work.</p>



<p>The best rehabs provide:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Multiple individual therapy sessions per week</li>



<li>Continuity with the same therapist throughout your stay (dedicated therapist)</li>



<li>Custom plans based on your story, not just your substance use</li>
</ul>



<p>You should never feel like just another client in a chair. Real healing happens when therapy meets you where you are &#8211; emotionally, neurologically and psychologically.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">3. Support for Mental Health and Neurodivergence</h4>



<p>Many people who struggle with addiction are also living with<strong> mental health conditions</strong>, like:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Anxiety</li>



<li>Depression</li>



<li>PTSD or C-PTSD</li>



<li>ADHD</li>



<li>Autism</li>



<li>OCD</li>
</ul>



<p>If a rehab doesn’t address these, relapse becomes far more likely. You can’t treat addiction without treating what’s underneath it.</p>



<p>Signs of a quality centre include:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Trained dual diagnosis clinicians</li>



<li>Therapies suited for trauma and neurodivergent processing</li>



<li>Medication reviews with psychiatry support (if appropriate)</li>



<li>Acceptance of clients with different brains &#8211; ADHD or autism without shame or misunderstanding</li>
</ul>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="768" src="https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/holistic-therapies-session-1-1024x768.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-45362" srcset="https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/holistic-therapies-session-1-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/holistic-therapies-session-1-300x225.jpg 300w, https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/holistic-therapies-session-1-768x576.jpg 768w, https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/holistic-therapies-session-1-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/holistic-therapies-session-1-400x300.jpg 400w, https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/holistic-therapies-session-1-30x23.jpg 30w, https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/holistic-therapies-session-1-13x10.jpg 13w, https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/holistic-therapies-session-1.webp 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">4. Trauma-Informed, Not Authoritarian</h4>



<p>Traditional rehab models work off a one-size-fits-all approach, but we now know this approach can be <strong>harmful</strong>, especially for people with trauma histories — which includes a large portion of those entering treatment.</p>



<p>The best rehabs today are trauma-informed. That means:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Clients are given choices and agency</li>



<li>Boundaries are clear but kind</li>



<li>Shame and blame are replaced with curiosity and compassion</li>



<li>Staff understand how trauma affects behaviour, relationships and recovery.</li>
</ul>



<p>If a rehab does not genuinely offer a range of therapeutic modalities or tailored one-to-one sessions, look elsewhere. </p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">5. Aftercare That Goes Beyond a Printout</h4>



<p>A rehab isn’t successful because someone stays sober during their time there. The real test comes <strong>after discharge</strong> &#8211; when routines fade, emotions return and real life starts again.</p>



<p>Top-quality centres build this into their programme from day one:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Structured aftercare plans</li>



<li>Return-to-work or reintegration support</li>



<li>Referrals to trusted therapists or support groups</li>



<li>Optional check-ins or alumni sessions</li>
</ul>



<p>Ask: “What happens when I leave?” The answer should include specifics &#8211; not vague promises.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">6. Transparent Pricing and Clear Communication</h4>



<p>If you have to ask three times to get a straight answer on price, or you’re being pressured into a deposit before seeing a contract, you’re not dealing with a rehab that values trust.</p>



<p>The best centres are up-front about:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Programme costs</li>



<li>What’s included (and what’s not)</li>



<li>Admissions criteria and limitations</li>



<li>Payment options or funding advice</li>
</ul>



<p>Even if a centre is expensive, <strong>honesty builds trust</strong> — and trust is essential to healing.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">7. A Real Environment for Recovery</h4>



<p>The physical environment matters — not because you need five-star luxury, but because recovery requires a setting where you can feel safe, grounded and human.</p>



<p>Look for:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Private, calm spaces (not overcrowded dorms)</li>



<li>Good food and sleep support</li>



<li>Opportunities for nature, creativity, or movement</li>



<li>Time for rest, not just therapy back-to-back</li>
</ul>



<p>Healing is holistic. The best centres create environments where people aren’t just sober &#8211; they’re supported to <em>feel safe in their own skin again.</em></p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">What to Watch Out For: Red Flags</h3>



<p>Unfortunately, not all treatment centres operate in your best interest.</p>



<p>Some warning signs to avoid:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Websites that don’t clearly name the rehab they’re promoting</li>



<li>Call centres that pressure you to book immediately</li>



<li>“Best of” lists with no transparent criteria or clinical evidence</li>



<li>Claims of high success rates without supporting evidence. </li>



<li>No mention of aftercare, trauma support or medical detox</li>
</ul>



<p>If you feel unsure, pause. A good admissions team will answer your questions with care, not urgency.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="650" src="https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/sound-therapy-1-e1743602552912-1024x650.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-46639" srcset="https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/sound-therapy-1-e1743602552912-1024x650.jpg 1024w, https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/sound-therapy-1-e1743602552912-300x190.jpg 300w, https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/sound-therapy-1-e1743602552912-768x488.jpg 768w, https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/sound-therapy-1-e1743602552912-1536x975.jpg 1536w, https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/sound-therapy-1-e1743602552912-473x300.jpg 473w, https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/sound-therapy-1-e1743602552912-30x19.jpg 30w, https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/sound-therapy-1-e1743602552912-16x10.jpg 16w, https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/sound-therapy-1-e1743602552912.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Why “Best” Depends on You</h2>



<p>It’s easy to fall into the trap of searching for the best rehab as if it were a hotel &#8211; scanning ratings, reading reviews, comparing amenities. But addiction treatment isn’t a consumer product. What works for one person may be completely wrong for someone else.</p>



<p>That’s why <strong>the best rehab is not the fanciest or most expensive &#8211; it’s the one that fits your unique needs</strong>. Your mental health, your trauma history, your personality, your learning style, your goals &#8211; all of these matter.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Questions to Ask Yourself Before Choosing a Rehab</h3>



<p>Before you choose where to go, ask yourself:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Do I need help detoxing safely from alcohol or drugs?</li>



<li>Do I need support for anxiety, trauma, or a diagnosis like ADHD?</li>



<li>Am I more comfortable in a calm, quiet setting or somewhere more social?</li>



<li>Do I want therapy that includes my family or focuses just on me?</li>



<li>Do I prefer structured routines, or do I need space and flexibility?</li>



<li>Have I tried rehab before? If so, what worked, and what didn’t?</li>
</ul>



<p>Answering these questions honestly will help you focus on <em>fit</em>, not reputation. A centre with a flashy name but no emotional safety may fail you. A quiet, ethical, trauma-informed rehab may help you finally feel safe enough to heal.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Why Abbington House Meets the Standard</h2>



<p>At Abbington House, we don’t claim to be the best rehab for everyone. But we’ve built a centre that honours the things that actually matter: <strong>safety, dignity, emotional depth, and whole-person healing</strong>.</p>



<p>If you’ve been looking for something different &#8211; something human, something real,  we might be the place for you.</p>



<p>Here’s what makes our approach unique:</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">1. <strong>Personalised Care That Respects Your Story</strong></h3>



<p>No two people get the same treatment plan here. We tailor your therapeutic treatment with your focal therapist. Whether you’re neurodivergent, trauma-affected, anxious, or simply exhausted, we adjust to meet your needs rather than forcing you to adjust to us.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">2. <strong>Safe, Medical Detox On-Site</strong></h3>



<p>Our detox process is supervised by experienced professionals. You’ll be monitored with care and compassion, with full medical support to ease withdrawal safely and gently.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">3. <strong>Deep, Trauma-Informed Therapy</strong></h3>



<p>We offer far more than just group work. Our experienced therapists provide multiple one-to-one sessions weekly, with training in:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Complex trauma</li>



<li>EMDR</li>



<li>Parts work/IFS</li>



<li>Grief and relational trauma</li>



<li>Your emotional safety comes first. We’ll never shame, push, or break you down to build you up.</li>
</ul>



<div class="wp-block-group is-nowrap is-layout-flex wp-container-core-group-is-layout-ad2f72ca wp-block-group-is-layout-flex">
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">4. <strong>Support for Neurodivergent Clients</strong></h3>
</div>



<div class="wp-block-group is-nowrap is-layout-flex wp-container-core-group-is-layout-ad2f72ca wp-block-group-is-layout-flex">
<p>Some of our clients come to us with ADHD, autism, or sensory regulation issues. We’ve created an environment that accommodates rather than pathologises:</p>
</div>



<div class="wp-block-group is-content-justification-left is-nowrap is-layout-flex wp-container-core-group-is-layout-f56a869c wp-block-group-is-layout-flex">
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Quiet spaces and predictable routines</li>



<li>Flexible therapy pacing</li>



<li>Clear communication and non-judgmental support</li>



<li>Gentle holistic therapies for nervous system regulation.</li>
</ul>
</div>



<p></p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">5. <strong>No Pressure. No Sales Tactics.</strong></h3>



<p>You won’t find pushy admissions calls here. We’ll never ask for money before you’re ready and we’ll give you clear, transparent information about what we offer, how much it costs, and what to expect. You deserve <strong>clarity, not coercion</strong>. We can even arrange for you to visit us first with your family to make sure we&#8217;re the best fit for you. </p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Making the Right Choice for You</h2>



<p>Choosing a rehab isn’t just about facilities and credentials. It’s about how a place makes you feel &#8211;  whether you sense, even from the first call, that you’re seen as a whole person, not just another admission.</p>



<p>If you&#8217;re not ready, that&#8217;s okay. If you&#8217;re unsure, we&#8217;re happy to talk without pressure. And if you’re comparing options, we’ll help you ask the right questions &#8211; even if it means you choose somewhere else.</p>



<p>Because <strong>the best rehabs don’t just treat addiction. They empower you to live a life worth living.</strong></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Ready to Talk?</h3>



<p>We’re here to answer your questions about our rehab programmes:</p>



<p><strong>Speak to a member of our team</strong> for confidential guidance<br><strong>Speak to us on Livechat</strong></p>



<p>You don&#8217;t have to know for sure. You just have to start asking.</p>



<p><strong><a href="/contact-us/">Contact us →</a></strong><br><strong><a href="/admissions/">Learn more about our admissions process →</a></strong></p>



<p><strong><a href="/residential-rehab/">View our rehab programme →</a></strong></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/rehab-advice/best-rehab-uk/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>When to Seek Help for Alcohol Addiction</title>
		<link>https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/alcohol-addiction/when-to-seek-help/</link>
					<comments>https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/alcohol-addiction/when-to-seek-help/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rob Lloyd]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 15:30:35 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Alcohol Addiction]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/?p=48642</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[How to know when drinking stops being ‘Normal’ and starts needing support.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">“Am I Drinking Too Much?”</h2>



<p>If you’re asking the question, the answer might matter more than you think.</p>



<p>Maybe your drinking doesn’t <em>look</em> like a problem. You still go to work. You take care of your kids. You haven’t “hit rock bottom.” But something feels… off. Maybe it’s the way you drink alone, or how anxious you feel when you try to stop. Or maybe someone’s mentioned it, and now you’re wondering.</p>



<p>This page is here to help you make sense of that quiet voice in your head &#8211; the one asking if it’s time to get help.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What Are the Signs I Might Need Help?</h2>



<p>You don’t need to be falling apart to be struggling. Here are some signs that your relationship with alcohol might be unhealthy:</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Emotional Signs</h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>You feel anxious, low, or irritable when you’re not drinking</li>



<li>You rely on alcohol to “take the edge off” or to feel like yourself</li>



<li>You drink after arguments, stress, or emotional triggers</li>
</ul>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Behavioural Signs</h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>You find it hard to stop once you start</li>



<li>You hide how much you drink or feel ashamed of it</li>



<li>You drink alone more often than socially</li>



<li>You’ve tried to cut down, but it didn’t stick</li>
</ul>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Physical Signs</h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>You’re feeling tired, shaky, or unwell after drinking</li>



<li>You’re waking up in the night or sweating</li>



<li>You’ve started drinking earlier in the day</li>



<li>Your tolerance has increased</li>
</ul>



<p>You don’t have to tick every box. Even <strong>one or two of these</strong> might mean it’s time to pause and look deeper. If you still need convincing, head over to our <a href="https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/alcohol-addiction/signs/" data-type="post" data-id="46272">signs of alcohol addiction</a> page. </p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">When Does Drinking Cross the Line?</h2>



<p>There isn’t one. Alcohol addiction doesn’t always arrive with a crash. Sometimes it creeps in slowly disguised as stress, burnout, loneliness, or even celebration.</p>



<p>What matters isn’t how your drinking compares to someone else’s.<br>What matters is <strong>how it’s affecting you</strong>:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Your health</li>



<li>Your relationships</li>



<li>Your work or finances</li>



<li>Your ability to feel okay without it</li>
</ul>



<p>If alcohol is starting to feel like something you <em>need</em> rather than something you <em>enjoy</em>, that’s a signal worth listening to.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Why It’s So Hard to Admit You Need Help</h2>



<p>Because we live in a culture where drinking is everywhere.</p>



<p>It’s how we socialise. Unwind. Celebrate. Cope.</p>



<p>It can feel like admitting “I need help” means admitting failure, weakness, or being <em>that</em> kind of person.</p>



<p>You’re not. You’re human. And if you’re even <em>thinking</em> about asking for help, you’re already showing strength.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">H2: What Happens If I Don’t Get Help?</h2>



<p>Everyone’s story is different, but here’s what we see over and over again:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Drinking escalates.</strong> Tolerance goes up. Mental health goes down.</li>



<li><strong>Relationships suffer.</strong> Communication breaks down. Trust is lost.</li>



<li><strong>Your body begins to show it.</strong> Sleep, liver, blood pressure, anxiety, depression.</li>



<li><strong>Your life shrinks.</strong> The things that used to matter start to fade.</li>
</ul>



<p>But here&#8217;s the other side of that:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-layout-flow wp-block-quote-is-layout-flow">
<p><strong>When you get help early, the turnaround is faster. The damage is less. The healing begins sooner.</strong></p>
</blockquote>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">You Don’t Have to Be “Bad Enough” to Get Help</h2>



<p>At Abbington House, we work with people from all walks of life, many of whom never saw themselves as “addicts.”</p>



<p>They’re:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Professionals holding down high-pressure jobs</li>



<li>Parents overwhelmed by stress and coping quietly</li>



<li>People with anxiety, ADHD, or unresolved trauma</li>



<li>Men and women whose drinking <em>never looked</em> like the stereotype</li>
</ul>



<p>You don’t have to fall apart before you reach out. You just have to be <strong>ready to feel better</strong>.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">When to Reach Out for Support</h2>



<p>Here’s the truth:</p>



<p>If you’ve been googling “am I drinking too much?”<br>If you’ve tried to cut down but couldn’t<br>If someone you trust has expressed concern<br>If alcohol feels more like a crutch than a choice<br>If you&#8217;re scared but curious about what life without it might feel like&#8230;</p>



<p>Then it might be time to talk to someone. Even just to explore it.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">How We Can Help at Abbington House</h2>



<p>We&#8217;re a <strong>trauma-informed, private alcohol rehab</strong> centre in <strong>Hertfordshire</strong>. Our team offers:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Free, no-pressure phone assessments</li>



<li>Personalised detox and rehab plans</li>



<li>Support for dual diagnosis (ADHD, anxiety, depression)</li>



<li>A warm, nurturing environment, not a hospital</li>



<li>Aftercare planning for long-term healing</li>
</ul>



<p>Whether you live in <strong>Stevenage, St Albans, Hatfield, or anywhere near Hertfordshire</strong>, we’re here to support you or a loved one. </p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Not Ready for Rehab? That’s Okay Too.</h2>



<p>We can still help.</p>



<p>Sometimes, the first step is <strong>just a conversation</strong>. One that doesn’t pressure you to decide today, but gives you clarity and space to explore.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">You’re Asking for a Reason</h2>



<p>You wouldn’t be on this page if something in you didn’t already know.</p>



<p>So here’s the next gentle step:</p>



<p><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/15.1.0/72x72/1f4de.png" alt="📞" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /> <strong>Call us for a confidential chat</strong><br><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/15.1.0/72x72/1f4da.png" alt="📚" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /> <strong>Or keep reading, thinking, and feeling it through</strong></p>



<p>You’re not alone and you’re not too late, but you don’t need to hit rock bottom to deserve help.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">More Reading</h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a class="" href="/alcohol-addiction/signs/">Signs of Alcohol Addiction</a></li>



<li><a class="" href="/alcohol-rehab/">Alcohol Rehab</a></li>



<li><a class="" href="/alcohol-rehab/detox/">Alcohol Detox</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/alcohol-addiction/when-to-seek-help/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Addiction in the Workplace</title>
		<link>https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/workplace/addiction-in-the-workplace/</link>
					<comments>https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/workplace/addiction-in-the-workplace/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ellyn Iacovou]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2025 12:07:03 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Workplace]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/?p=48055</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Workplace addiction is a growing issue in the UK, affecting productivity, safety, and employee wellbeing. Whether it’s alcohol, prescription medication, or other substances, addiction doesn’t discriminate by job.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[		<div data-elementor-type="wp-post" data-elementor-id="48055" class="elementor elementor-48055" data-elementor-post-type="post">
				<div class="elementor-element elementor-element-34ca5262 e-flex e-con-boxed cmsmasters-block-default e-con e-parent" data-id="34ca5262" data-element_type="container">
					<div class="e-con-inner">
				<div class="elementor-element elementor-element-71fb64e0 cmsmasters-block-default cmsmasters-sticky-default elementor-widget elementor-widget-text-editor" data-id="71fb64e0" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="text-editor.default">
				<div class="elementor-widget-container">
									
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">It might start with a few drinks after work. Or using something to stay focused, sleep better, or just get through the day. Over time, it becomes harder to cope without it and easier to hide your struggle behind deadlines, meetings and long work hours.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Workplace addiction is a growing issue in the UK, affecting productivity, safety and employee wellbeing. And the thing is, it doesn’t always look obvious. It can affect anyone, whether you&#8217;re in a boardroom, behind a till, on a building site or working from home. Job title doesn’t protect you from burnout, stress or the pull of something that promises relief.</span></p>
<p>This page will explore how addiction manifests in the workplace, the signs to look for, the legal and ethical obligations of employers and what support is available.</p>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What Is Workplace Addiction?</h2>

<p>Workplace addiction refers to a pattern of substance use that negatively affects a person&#8217;s performance or behaviour at work. This may involve:</p>

<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Drinking alcohol during working hours or showing up hungover</li>

<li>Misusing prescription drugs to manage stress or stay alert</li>

<li>Taking illicit substances while working remotely or on-site</li>

<li>Engaging in compulsive behaviours like gambling or porn use during breaks.</li>
</ul>

<p>While addiction is a personal health issue, its impact often spills over into work leading to reduced productivity, damaged relationships and even safety risks in high-stakes industries.</p>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Why Is Addiction Common in the Workplace?</h2>

<p>Several work-related factors can contribute to the development of an addiction:</p>

<h3 class="wp-block-heading">1. <strong>High Stress and Pressure</strong></h3>

<p>Tight deadlines, long hours, or high-risk environments can push employees to self-medicate with substances to cope.</p>

<h3 class="wp-block-heading">2. <strong>Workplace Culture</strong></h3>

<p>Some professions normalise heavy drinking or ‘work hard, play hard’ mentalities, especially in sectors like finance, construction, marketing or hospitality.</p>

<h3 class="wp-block-heading">3. <strong>Isolation</strong></h3>

<p>Remote working or travel roles can lead to loneliness, which increases the risk of substance misuse as a form of emotional escape.</p>

<h3 class="wp-block-heading">4. <strong>Access to Substances</strong></h3>

<p>Certain jobs provide easier access to medications or chemicals, particularly in healthcare, laboratories or manual trades.</p>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Signs of Addiction in Employees or Colleagues</h2>

<p>Identifying addiction in the workplace isn’t always straightforward. It often develops slowly and can be well-hidden.</p>

<p><strong>Behavioural signs:</strong></p>

<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Frequent lateness or absenteeism</li>

<li>Mood swings, irritability, or emotional outbursts</li>

<li>Falling behind on tasks or missing deadlines</li>

<li>Avoidance of meetings or team activities.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Physical signs:</strong></p>

<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Smelling of alcohol</li>

<li>Drowsiness or hyperactivity</li>

<li>Poor hygiene or noticeable weight changes.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Performance signs:</strong></p>

<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Drop in quality of work</li>

<li>Frequent mistakes or lapses in judgment</li>

<li>Difficulty concentrating or following instructions.</li>
</ul>

<p>If multiple signs appear over time, it usually points to a deeper issue.</p>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">How Addiction Affects the Workplace</h2>

<p>The cost of workplace addiction isn’t just personal—it affects everyone around the individual.</p>

<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Financial impact:</strong> UK businesses lose billions yearly in absenteeism, accidents, and lost productivity related to substance misuse.</li>

<li><strong>Safety concerns:</strong> In industries like transport or construction, working while impaired puts lives at risk.</li>

<li><strong>Morale and culture:</strong> Teams may feel strained, frustrated, or resentful when a colleague isn’t pulling their weight.</li>

<li><strong>Reputation:</strong> Misconduct, public incidents, or legal issues stemming from addiction can damage an organisation’s brand.</li>
</ul>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Your Responsibilities as an Employer</h2>

<p>In the UK, employers have both legal and ethical responsibilities to address workplace addiction.</p>

<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Health and Safety at Work Act (1974):</strong> Employers must ensure a safe working environment, which includes managing the risks posed by impaired staff.</li>

<li><strong>Equality Act (2010):</strong> If addiction is linked to a disability or mental health condition, employers may need to make reasonable adjustments.</li>

<li><strong>Duty of care:</strong> Failing to support an employee with addiction can lead to legal disputes or damage to company culture.</li>
</ul>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">How Employers Can Support Employees with Addiction</h2>

<p>A compassionate approach is more effective than punishment. Here’s how to support employees struggling with addiction:</p>

<h3 class="wp-block-heading">1. <strong>Create a Clear Substance Use Policy</strong></h3>

<p>Lay out expectations, procedures for reporting, and available support. Make it part of on-boarding and staff training.</p>

<h3 class="wp-block-heading">2. <strong>Encourage Disclosure Without Shame</strong></h3>

<p>Build a workplace culture where people feel safe to seek help early, before it affects performance.</p>

<h3 class="wp-block-heading">3. <strong>Provide Access to Professional Help</strong></h3>

<p>Partner with rehab clinics, counsellors, or Employee Assistance Programmes (EAPs). Offer paid leave or flexible hours during treatment if possible.</p>

<h3 class="wp-block-heading">4. <strong>Train Managers to Spot the Signs</strong></h3>

<p>Equip line managers and HR staff with the tools to identify and respond sensitively to addiction-related behaviours.</p>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">When a Colleague Is Struggling</h2>

<p>You might suspect a colleague is misusing substances but feel unsure about how to help. Here’s what you can do:</p>

<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Speak privately and express concern without judgment</li>

<li>Encourage them to speak to HR or a mental health lead</li>

<li>Don’t cover up or enable harmful behaviour, act in everyone’s best interest</li>

<li>If you feel unsafe, report the situation through official channels.</li>
</ul>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Treatment Options for Workplace Addiction</h2>

<p>The good news: addiction is treatable, and recovery is possible with the right support.</p>

<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Private Rehab</strong></h3>

<p>Fast-access treatment in a confidential setting, often tailored for professionals. Ideal for those needing structured care.</p>

<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Outpatient Support</strong></h3>

<p>Flexible help via NHS or local services, suitable for those managing mild or early-stage addiction.</p>

<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>Workplace Recovery Coaching</strong></h3>

<p>Some companies fund return-to-work coaching, therapy, or ongoing support through EAPs.</p>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Real-Life Story: Recovery While Employed</h2>

<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-layout-flow wp-block-quote-is-layout-flow">
<p>“I was working 60-hour weeks and drinking every night to cope. I hid it well until I didn’t. My boss gave me a lifeline instead of firing me. Rehab changed everything, and now I support others facing the same battle”.</p>

<p>– James, Marketing Director, age 37</p>
</blockquote>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Summary: Building a Recovery-Friendly Workplace</h2>

<p>Addiction in the workplace isn’t a moral failing, it’s a health condition. When employers respond with support instead of stigma, everyone benefits.</p>

<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Early intervention saves lives</li>

<li>Recovery is possible without career sacrifice</li>

<li>Compassionate workplaces improve morale, loyalty, and safety.</li>
</ul>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Additional Reading</h2>

<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/alcohol-addiction/mental-health/">Alcohol Addiction and Mental Health</a></li>

<li><a href="https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/private-rehab/what-is-private-rehab/" data-type="link" data-id="https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/private-rehab/what-is-private-rehab/">Private Rehab Options and Benefits</a></li>

<li><a href="/what-is-addiction/">Understanding Addiction: A Simple Guide</a></li>
</ul>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">FAQs About Addiction in the Workplace</h2>
<div id="rank-math-faq" class="rank-math-block">
<div class="rank-math-list ">
<div id="faq-question-1744978034004" class="rank-math-list-item">
<h3 class="rank-math-question ">Is addiction considered a disability in the UK?</h3>
<div class="rank-math-answer ">

<p>Addiction itself is not classified as a disability under the Equality Act 2010, but if it leads to mental health problems then it would be classified as a disability. </p>

</div>
</div>
<div id="faq-question-1744978039464" class="rank-math-list-item">
<h3 class="rank-math-question ">Can I get fired for addiction?</h3>
<div class="rank-math-answer ">

<p>Employers must follow fair procedures. In many cases, seeking or reaching out for help before job performance is affected can protect your position.</p>

</div>
</div>
<div id="faq-question-1744978048239" class="rank-math-list-item">
<h3 class="rank-math-question ">Should employers offer paid time off for rehab?</h3>
<div class="rank-math-answer ">

<p>While not required by law, many progressive employers offer flexible leave as part of a health-based recovery policy. </p>

</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<h3 class="wp-block-heading"> </h3>

<p> </p>
								</div>
				</div>
					</div>
				</div>
				</div>
		]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/workplace/addiction-in-the-workplace/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>What Is Addiction? A Simple, Easy to Understand Guide</title>
		<link>https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/addiction-guides/what-is-addiction/</link>
					<comments>https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/addiction-guides/what-is-addiction/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rob Lloyd]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2025 10:08:37 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Addiction Guides]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/?p=48015</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Addiction is when a person keeps doing something - even if it’s hurting them - because their brain and body have come to rely on it. It’s not about being weak or lacking in willpower. It is an illness.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[		<div data-elementor-type="wp-post" data-elementor-id="48015" class="elementor elementor-48015" data-elementor-post-type="post">
				<div class="elementor-element elementor-element-3bf12d5 e-flex e-con-boxed cmsmasters-block-default e-con e-parent" data-id="3bf12d5" data-element_type="container">
					<div class="e-con-inner">
				<div class="elementor-element elementor-element-48de2705 cmsmasters-block-default cmsmasters-sticky-default elementor-widget elementor-widget-text-editor" data-id="48de2705" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="text-editor.default">
				<div class="elementor-widget-container">
									
<p><strong>Note from Author</strong>: I wrote this simple, easy to read guide so that all age demographics can understand the definition of addiction which affects people from all walks of life.</p>

<p><strong>Addiction</strong> is when a person keeps doing something &#8211; even if it’s hurting them &#8211; because their brain and body have come to rely on it. It’s not about being weak or lacking in willpower. It is an illness.</p>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Understanding Addiction</h2>

<p>Imagine your brain has a “feel-good button”. Every time you do something fun &#8211; like playing a game, eating cake, or laughing with friends &#8211; it presses that button, and you feel happy.</p>

<p>But with addiction, that button gets stuck. Your brain starts demanding the thing that made it feel good &#8211; again and again &#8211; even if that thing is hurting you.</p>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What Can Someone Be Addicted To?</h2>

<p>Addiction isn’t just about drugs or alcohol. It can happen with almost anything that lights up that “feel-good” part of the brain &#8211; a neurotransmitter known as <strong>dopamine</strong>.</p>

<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Substance addictions</strong>: alcohol, prescription drugs, cocaine, cannabis, nicotine</li>

<li><strong>Behavioural addictions</strong>: gambling, gaming, shopping, food, porn</li>
</ul>

<p>It becomes a problem when the person can’t stop &#8211; even when it starts damaging their health, relationships, or life.</p>

<p>The following video by Andreas Hykade perfectly illustrates what addiction looks like.</p>

<div class="wp-block-columns is-layout-flex wp-container-core-columns-is-layout-9d6595d7 wp-block-columns-is-layout-flex">
<div class="wp-block-column is-layout-flow wp-block-column-is-layout-flow" style="flex-basis: 100%;">
<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio">
<div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6CyecTodsuQ</div>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">The Bio-Psychosocial Model</h2>

<p>This is a fancy way of saying: addiction is caused by a mix of biology, psychology, and social factors.</p>

<h3 class="wp-block-heading">1. Biological Factors</h3>

<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Some people are born more sensitive to addiction.</li>

<li>Drugs and alcohol change how the brain works, especially the dopamine system (the feel-good chemical).</li>

<li>Over time, the brain starts needing more and more to feel “normal”.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Example</strong>: If someone drinks every night, their body adjusts. When they stop, they may feel anxious, shaky, or even sick. This is known as <strong>withdrawal</strong>.</p>

<h3 class="wp-block-heading">2. Psychological Factors</h3>

<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Addiction often starts as a way to cope with pain.</li>

<li>Trauma, anxiety, stress, and low self-worth are all common triggers.</li>

<li>People may use substances to numb their feelings or escape reality.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Example</strong>: Someone with painful childhood memories might drink or use drugs to block out the emotions they don’t know how to handle.</p>

<h3 class="wp-block-heading">3. Social Factors</h3>

<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Our environment plays a big role.</li>

<li>Friends, family, and even jobs can influence our behaviour.</li>

<li>Stress, poverty, loneliness, or being around others who use can make addiction more likely.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Example</strong>: If everyone around you drinks or uses drugs, it can feel “normal” even if it’s harmful.</p>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Why Don’t People Just Stop?</h2>

<p>This is one of the biggest myths about addiction.</p>

<p>It’s <strong>not about willpower</strong>. Addiction changes the brain. Stopping can feel impossible without help because:</p>

<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>The brain has rewired to <em>need</em> the substance</li>

<li>Withdrawal symptoms are painful and scary</li>

<li>The substance became their main way to cope</li>

<li>Shame makes people hide or avoid asking for help</li>
</ul>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">How Do People Get Better?</h2>

<p>Addiction recovery is about <strong>healing</strong>, not just quitting. At <strong>Abbington House</strong>, we help people:</p>

<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Understand <em>why</em> they became addicted</li>

<li>Process past trauma and pain</li>

<li>Learn healthy ways to deal with stress and emotions</li>

<li>Rebuild confidence and trust in themselves</li>
</ul>

<p>Recovery isn’t a one-size-fits-all journey. That’s why our approach is <strong>trauma-informed</strong>, <strong>compassionate</strong>, and <strong>completely personalised</strong>.</p>

<p><a href="/residential-rehab/">Learn more about our residential rehab programme</a></p>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">“It’s Not Who I Am. It’s What I’ve Been Through.”</h2>

<p>We hear this all the time and it’s true.</p>

<p>Addiction doesn’t mean someone is broken. It means they’ve been through things that hurt them deeply, and they found a way (even if harmful) to survive. Put simply, the addiction is acting as a solution to a problem.</p>

<p>With the right support, people rediscover who they really are and start living life on their terms again.</p>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Additional Reading</h2>

<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="/alcohol-addiction/what-is-alcohol-addiction/">Alcohol Addiction: The Complete Guide</a></li>

<li><a href="https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/addiction-guides/understanding-trauma-and-addiction/">How Trauma and Addiction Are Connected</a></li>

<li><a href="https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/addiction-help/help-for-loved-ones/">Help for a Loved One</a></li>

<li><a href="https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/addiction-help/help-for-myself/">Help for Myself</a></li>
</ul>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Frequently Asked Questions</h2>

<h3 class="wp-block-heading">What is the best way to explain addiction to a child?</h3>

<p>Say: <em>“It’s when someone keeps doing something &#8211; even if it hurts them &#8211; because their brain got used to it and now thinks they need it”</em>.</p>

<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Is addiction a choice?</h3>

<p>The first use might be a choice, but addiction itself is not. It changes the brain, and that makes stopping incredibly difficult without support.</p>

<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Can trauma cause addiction?</h3>

<p>Yes. Many people who struggle with addiction have experienced trauma like abuse, neglect, bullying, or loss.</p>

<h3 class="wp-block-heading">What’s the difference between a bad habit and addiction?</h3>

<p>A habit can usually be broken with effort. Addiction keeps going even when someone wants to stop because it involves physical and emotional dependence.</p>

<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Where can I get help in the UK?</h3>

<p>You can speak to your GP, find a private rehab like <a href="https://www.abbingtonhouse.co.uk">Abbington House</a>, or contact addiction charities like Change Grow Live or Turning Point.</p>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />
<p><strong>Need Support?</strong></p>

<p>Whether you’re struggling yourself or worried about someone else, <strong>you’re not alone</strong>. At Abbington House, we’re here to help without judgment.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.abbingtonhouse.co.uk/contact">Contact us today for confidential advice</a></p>

<p> </p>
								</div>
				</div>
					</div>
				</div>
				</div>
		]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/addiction-guides/what-is-addiction/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ADHD and Addiction: Why Both Conditions are Deeply Connected</title>
		<link>https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/addiction-neurodivergence/adhd-and-addiction/</link>
					<comments>https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/addiction-neurodivergence/adhd-and-addiction/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ellyn Iacovou]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 09 Apr 2025 15:26:38 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Addiction & Neurodivergence]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/?p=47358</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[We’re Rob and Ellyn – two people with ADHD who’ve also experienced addiction firsthand. Between us, we’ve spent close to a decade working in the addiction treatment field: Ellyn as a writer creating content for mental health and recovery services, and Rob in digital strategy and search.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">ADHD and Addiction Through Lived Experience</h2>



<p>We’re Rob and Ellyn &#8211; two people with ADHD who’ve experienced the chaos of neurodivergence and addiction firsthand. We&#8217;ve both worked in the addiction treatment sector for nearly a decade. Ellyn &#8211; a writer who’s delivered content for hundreds of mental health and recovery campaigns &#8211; and Rob &#8211; on digital search and web development campaigns. Together, we’ve seen addiction up close, both professionally and personally.</p>



<p>We didn’t meet in a clinical setting; we met building marketing campaigns and very soon, we realised we were living parallel lives: Rob, with a history of compulsive behaviours like gaming, workaholism and dopamine chasing. Ellyn, with undiagnosed ADHD until her 30s, masking for years through perfectionism, emotional burnout, and using substances to soothe internal overwhelm. For Ellyn, going to rehab was the beginning of her ADHD discovery.</p>



<p>We’ve seen how ADHD and compulsive behaviours are often the norm &#8211; and for those who are exploring the possibility of treatment for addiction alongside ADHD, we hope the information found on this page helps you or a loved one seek the right support.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Let’s Start With the Facts: ADHD and Addiction Are Linked</h2>



<p>The research is clear and consistent. If you live with ADHD, your risk of developing a substance use disorder is significantly higher.</p>



<figure>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th><em>Key Statistic</em></th>
<th><em>What It Means</em></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>People with ADHD are 2.5–3x more likely to develop an addiction</td>
<td>ADHD is one of the strongest predictors of SUD</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Up to 25% of people in addiction treatment also meet the criteria for ADHD</td>
<td>Many remain undiagnosed</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Nicotine, alcohol, cannabis, and stimulants are the most commonly misused substances in ADHD</td>
<td>These substances often provide short-term relief from ADHD symptoms</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ADHD is often missed in women and adults</td>
<td>Especially those with high masking abilities or internalised symptoms</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</figure>



<p>But this isn’t just about statistics; this is about the real people &#8211; like us &#8211; who live with fast brains and nervous systems that rarely rest. People who didn’t choose addiction but found themselves pulled toward anything that offered even a moment of relief.</p>



<hr />



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Rob: “I am always going to be at risk of addiction”</h2>



<p>For me (Rob), ADHD has always been a loud presence. I was diagnosed at 14, back when people thought ADHD was just about fidgeting or being disruptive in school (I was both of those things, so I totally get it). But it didn&#8217;t always look like that. It looked like gaming for 10 hours straight, feeling as though I needed to fix everything, working until I crashed, and needing something to stimulate my mind or sedate it &#8211; mostly nicotine.</p>



<p>I wasn’t chasing highs. I was chasing stillness. That&#8217;s the key part I want everyone to understand. Addiction is often viewed through a lens of destruction and suffering &#8211; which it absolutely is &#8211; but there&#8217;s another way to also view it. Addiction is trying to solve something, and for people like us living with ADHD, the solution is very much intertwined with the problem &#8211; both ADHD and addiction affect dopamine reward systems.</p>



<hr />



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Ellyn: “I masked so well, I didn’t know it was ADHD”</h2>



<p>For me (Ellyn), ADHD was a ghost. It was there &#8211; always &#8211; but no one could name it. I was the people pleaser and sensitive one who got told to toughen up. I wasn’t loud or disruptive, but my brain never stopped.</p>



<p>By the time I was in my twenties, I was juggling emotional dysregulation, insomnia, anxiety and substance abuse issues. I was writing content in active addiction, and at the time, I had no way of coping without it.</p>



<p>When I finally went to rehab and got diagnosed with ADHD, everything clicked &#8211; including my history of compulsive behaviours as emotional regulation tools.</p>



<p>And like Rob, the solution of self-medicating solved one problem, but created more elsewhere.</p>



<hr />



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Why ADHD Makes You More Vulnerable to Addiction</h2>



<p>People think addiction is a moral failing or a lack of willpower. Sadly, there are still many people who remain completely ignorant to what ADHD actually is.</p>



<p>Addiction, especially for ADHD brains, is a form of self-regulation &#8211; but it&#8217;s more than that &#8211; having ADHD puts you at greater risk of other traumatic events too.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">1. <em>Dopamine Dysregulation</em></h3>



<p>ADHD affects the dopamine system, which is the brain’s reward and motivation pathway. That means we’re often:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Under-stimulated</li>



<li>Bored quickly</li>



<li>Prone to impulsivity</li>



<li>Constantly seeking novelty</li>
</ul>



<p>Substances like alcohol, cannabis or stimulants? They offer <em>immediate relief</em> &#8211; not just emotionally, but chemically.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">2. <em>Emotional Dysregulation &amp; Trauma</em></h3>



<p>Many of us with ADHD experience rejection-sensitive dysphoria (RSD), intense emotions, and a history of being misunderstood. These emotional patterns can lead to:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Social withdrawal</li>



<li>Low self-worth</li>



<li>High anxiety</li>



<li>Burnout cycles</li>
</ul>



<p>And if trauma is layered in (which it often is), we’re even more vulnerable. <a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC5518307/pdf/nihms878682.pdf" data-type="link" data-id="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC5518307/pdf/nihms878682.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Studies show</a> a strong overlap between developmental trauma, ADHD, and addictive behaviour.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">3. <em>Impulsivity and Poor Inhibitory Control</em></h3>



<p>ADHD makes it harder to pause between thought and action. This means we’re more likely to:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Try substances earlier</li>



<li>Use them in riskier ways</li>



<li>Struggle with stopping, even when we want to</li>
</ul>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Managing Compulsive Behaviour and ADHD Without Shame</h2>



<p>We’re not here to hand out recovery tips; ADHD doesn’t work like that because what helps one person might overwhelm another. But what we can offer is transparency &#8211; the messy, imperfect, lived-in kind that lets you know you’re not alone.</p>



<p>We both manage compulsive behaviours in our lives &#8211; sometimes well, other times not. But every time we hit a wall, we learn something new about what we need.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Rob: Replacing the Rush Without Replacing the Pattern</h3>



<p>I used to think the goal was to eliminate all dopamine-seeking. To stop chasing productivity highs, stop bingeing YouTube at 1am, stop gaming when I was overwhelmed. But that just made me feel worse. It added another layer of pressure. Self-awareness and self-compassion are two areas I would always recommend working on.</p>



<p>What I needed was to find balance, replacing some of the rush with something nourishing &#8211; not to eliminate the need altogether.</p>



<p>Now I use:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><em>Movement</em>&nbsp;to regulate overstimulation – walking/exercise clears mental fog</li>



<li><em>Box breathing</em> when I catch that “must-scroll-now” feeling &#8211; it gives that extra space to ask myself: &#8220;is this really what I need right now?&#8221;</li>



<li><em>Low-stimulation activities</em> &#8211; sometimes I like to sit in a darkened room and listen to music, for others that can be a weighted blanket</li>



<li><em>Permission to do nothing</em>, which paradoxically resets me more than anything else</li>
</ul>



<p>The key for me is recognising the urge and <em>responding instead of reacting</em>. That’s still hard. But when I treat myself like someone worth supporting &#8211; not correcting &#8211; I am much kinder to myself.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Ellyn: Gentle Structure, Not Self-Punishment</h3>



<p>Having children makes it harder to have those quieter times to switch off, which can often lead to overstimulation and an increased need for sugary foods, screens, doom scrolling, sleep avoidance. Instead of viewing these things as self-sabotage, I see it as a need to create space for recovery.</p>



<p>Here’s what I’ve built for myself:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Planning backwards: Instead of making long lists, I log what I actually did each day &#8211; it builds momentum and reduces the likelihood of negative self-feelings.</li>



<li>Scheduled time for myself in the evenings: Once the kids go to bed, that is my time to do what I need to do.</li>
</ul>



<p>I don’t aim for perfect weeks anymore. I aim for self-trust. That’s what keeps my compulsions quieter.</p>



<hr />



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Behavioural Addictions People with ADHD Commonly Face</h2>



<p>Not everyone with ADHD misuses substances. But many of us walk the tightrope of socially sanctioned compulsions &#8211; behaviours that look “normal,” even admirable, until they start taking over our lives.</p>



<p>Let’s name a few:</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">1. <em>Workaholism</em></h3>



<p>I (Rob) have fallen victim to this cycle many times before. There is often a fine line between passion and addiction for me. Workaholism looks like:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Overdelivering to avoid being seen as lazy</li>



<li>Tying your worth to productivity</li>



<li>Never switching off, even when your body is exhausted.</li>
</ul>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">2. <em>Gaming</em></h3>



<p>I (Rob) spent most of my childhood playing videogames, and it&#8217;s obvious to me why they are so appealing to the ADHD brain. Fast feedback, clear goals, achievement unlocked &#8211; it’s an ADHD paradise. But when 30 minutes becomes 6 hours at 3am. It starts to cost more than it gives.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">3. <em>Food and Binge Eating</em></h3>



<p>We both know the sugar-caffeine-regret loop well. For many, food is comfort, stimulation and control. But it’s also a survival mechanism &#8211; especially when emotional regulation is low and stimulation is scarce. Binge eating is cheap, convenient and tastes good at the time.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">4. <em>Impulse Spending</em></h3>



<p>Quick dopamine. Instant gratification. Regret later. For ADHD brains, online shopping hits hard and often. It’s not about materialism, it’s about relief.</p>



<p>If you recognise yourself here, please know: this isn’t a character flaw. It’s a coping mechanism in disguise. You’re managing chaos the best way you know how. That awareness is the first step.</p>



<hr />



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What Has Actually Helped Us Living with ADHD and Addiction</h2>



<p>We can’t give you a recovery formula, but here are the patterns that moved us forward:</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">1. <em>Self-Compassion &gt; Self-Discipline</em></h3>



<p>ADHD culture loves “hacks” and “systems,” but they’re useless if they’re built on self-loathing. When we stopped treating ourselves like projects and started treating ourselves like people, everything changed.</p>



<p><em>Try this reframing:</em></p>



<figure>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Instead of…</th>
<th>Say…</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>“I failed again.”</td>
<td>“I need to improve my system to better support me.”</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>“I’m too lazy.”</td>
<td>“I’m overwhelmed and need a reset.”</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>“I should have done more.”</td>
<td>“What I did today was enough.”</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</figure>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">2. <em>Co-Regulation Over Isolation</em></h3>



<p>Recovery from anything is brutal when done alone. ADHD makes us prone to isolation spirals, where shame keeps us quiet and disconnection fuels compulsivity.</p>



<p>We both rely on:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Friends who understand executive dysfunction</li>



<li>Mentors or therapists who validate our wiring</li>



<li>Co-working, body-doubling, or parallel play</li>
</ul>



<p>The message here: connection heals more than willpower ever will, and that&#8217;s true for both ADHD and addiction.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">3. <em>Micro-Decisions Create Macro-Change</em></h3>



<p>You don’t need to transform your life in 30 days. You need to pick one corner of chaos and shine a light on it.</p>



<p>Here are small things that helped us regain control:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Picking up a messy room corner while listening to a podcast</li>



<li>Switching coffee to water when anxiety hit (we don&#8217;t recommend alcohol, obviously)</li>



<li>Scheduling one thing instead of five</li>



<li>Sending a voice note when we don&#8217;t feel like talking to people</li>
</ul>



<hr />



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Why We Wrote this Article on Addiction and ADHD</h2>



<p>We’re not experts with letters after our names. But we’re ADHD adults with lived experience who’ve built careers in addiction treatment, marketing, content and storytelling. We regularly meet people just like us &#8211; misunderstood, sensitive and in need of something to help them get through the day.</p>



<p>If you or someone you care about has ADHD and are exploring addiction treatment options, it&#8217;s important to remember that you’re living in a world that wasn’t designed with your brain in mind. But the conversation is changing, and there are clinics that will build a recovery path that fits your neurodivergent needs.&nbsp;</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">If You Need Help with ADHD and Addiction</h2>



<p><p>The line between compulsive behaviour and addiction isn’t always clear &#8211; especially when ADHD is involved. Too often, people like us are either told we’re “not bad enough” or &#8220;beyond help&#8221;, and that&#8217;s often the surface-level paradox of ADHD. We either keep pushing, keep performing or keep burning out.</p>
<p>But the truth is, you don’t need to be addicted to alcohol or drugs to deserve support. If your behaviours – whatever they are – are controlling you, draining you, or making your world feel smaller, that’s reason enough to reach out</p></p>



<p><p data-start="820" data-end="1049">At Abbington House, ADHD isn’t treated as a side note. Their programme is designed for people who live with overlapping challenges like ours &#8211; people whose addiction and mental health needs don’t fit neatly into a generic model.</p>
<p data-start="1051" data-end="1145">There is a better way to live. You’re not too much. You’re not too late. And you’re not alone.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/addiction-neurodivergence/adhd-and-addiction/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Addiction Help for a Loved One</title>
		<link>https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/addiction-help/help-for-loved-ones/</link>
					<comments>https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/addiction-help/help-for-loved-ones/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ellyn Iacovou]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 09 Apr 2025 15:05:36 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Addiction Help]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/?p=47419</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[When someone you love is struggling with addiction, it can feel like you’re carrying the weight of two lives.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[		<div data-elementor-type="wp-post" data-elementor-id="47419" class="elementor elementor-47419" data-elementor-post-type="post">
				<div class="elementor-element elementor-element-3a3f32c6 e-flex e-con-boxed cmsmasters-block-default e-con e-parent" data-id="3a3f32c6" data-element_type="container">
					<div class="e-con-inner">
				<div class="elementor-element elementor-element-7d5dd9a8 cmsmasters-block-default cmsmasters-sticky-default elementor-widget elementor-widget-text-editor" data-id="7d5dd9a8" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="text-editor.default">
				<div class="elementor-widget-container">
									
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Supporting Someone with Addiction Without Losing Yourself Along the Way</h2>

<p>When someone you love is struggling with addiction, it can feel like you’re carrying the weight of two lives. You want to help them, but you don’t know how. You want them to get better, but you’re not sure they even see the problem.</p>

<p>At Abbington House, we support families, partners, and friends who are navigating this difficult path. Whether your loved one is ready for rehab, in denial or somewhere in between, this isn&#8217;t something you have to do alone.</p>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Their Addiction Affects You Too</h3>

<p>Addiction affects more than one person. It impacts the people closest to them emotionally, mentally and sometimes even physically.</p>

<p>You might be feeling:</p>

<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Helpless, watching them spiral but not knowing how to stop it</li>

<li>Angry or resentful, after broken promises and repeated let-downs</li>

<li>Confused, unsure what’s addiction and what’s choice</li>

<li>Exhausted, trying to ‘manage’ it behind closed doors</li>

<li>Scared of what might happen next, or how far things might go.</li>
</ul>

<p>These feelings are completely valid, and they are not signs of weakness or failure. They show that you care deeply, but you deserve support too.</p>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">When Should You Reach Out?</h3>

<p>You don’t need to wait for things to get worse before you seek help. In fact, the sooner you understand your options, the better prepared you’ll be for them and for yourself.</p>

<p>Common signs your loved one may need professional support:</p>

<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>They’ve tried to quit drinking or using drugs, but can’t</li>

<li>Their behaviour has changed (mood swings, secrecy, anger)</li>

<li>They’ve withdrawn from friends, work, or family responsibilities</li>

<li>You find yourself constantly worrying, watching, or ‘cleaning up’ after them</li>

<li>You’re walking on eggshells more often than not</li>

<li>You feel as though the person you once knew is completely different</li>

<li>You are considering leaving them, but the pain of watching them suffer leaves you in a difficult position.</li>
</ul>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">How We Can Help You and Them</h3>

<p>Abbington House is a trauma-informed, private rehab centre based in Hertfordshire. We offer a safe, professional space where people can recover and families can find relief.</p>

<p>When you contact us, we can:</p>

<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Help you understand whether rehab is the right next step</li>

<li>Talk you through how our programme works</li>

<li>Guide you on how to approach a conversation with your loved one</li>

<li>Support you emotionally, even if they’re not ready for help yet</li>
</ul>

<p>We never pressure anyone into treatment. Trying to force someone into treatment is likely to yield little benefit, but we can offer the necessary guidance for putting in place important boundaries. This is just as much about protecting you as it is them.</p>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">How to Talk to Your Loved One About Rehab</h3>

<p>We know how hard these conversations can be. That’s why we’re here to help you prepare for them.</p>

<p>Some helpful tips include:</p>

<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Choose the right time</strong>: Avoid high-stress or intoxicated moments</li>

<li><strong>Lead with concern, not accusation</strong>: e.g. &#8220;I&#8217;m worried about you&#8221; instead of &#8220;You need to stop&#8221;</li>

<li><strong>Offer information, not ultimatums</strong>: Let them know help is available &#8211; but avoid triggering defensiveness at this stage</li>

<li><strong>Focus on impact</strong>: Gently explain how it’s affecting you and others</li>

<li><strong>Have support in place</strong>: We can be that support if you need us.</li>
</ul>

<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-layout-flow wp-block-quote-is-layout-flow">
<p>&gt; <a href="/admissions/">Learn about our admissions process</a></p>
</blockquote>

<h3 class="wp-block-heading">What If They Say No?</h3>

<p>Not everyone is ready the first time the subject comes up or even the 50th time. That doesn’t mean you’ve failed. And it doesn’t mean they’ll never change.</p>

<p>Often, just planting the seed gently and compassionately is enough to start the process.</p>

<p>You can still:</p>

<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Set boundaries to protect yourself</li>

<li>Get emotional support from professionals</li>

<li>Stay connected to us, so when they are ready, you know what to do next.</li>
</ul>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Our Promise to Families</h3>

<p>At Abbington House, we never forget that addiction affects families too. That’s why we treat you with the same care, honesty, and respect that we offer to our residents.</p>

<p>Whether your loved one enters treatment with us or not, we will support you as you navigate this complex journey.</p>

<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-layout-flow wp-block-quote-is-layout-flow">
<p>“It was a huge relief to speak to someone who actually listened. They didn’t push. They helped me understand what was happening and what I could do without losing myself.”</p>

<p>&#8211; Partner of a former resident.</p>
</blockquote>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">You’re Not Alone in This</h3>

<p>Supporting someone with addiction is hard. But you don’t have to carry that burden alone.</p>

<p>Let’s talk about what’s going on, what’s possible, and what help could look like.</p>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />
<p><strong>Explore next:</strong></p>

<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/residential-rehab/family-therapy/">Family Support in Rehab →</a></li>
</ul>
								</div>
				</div>
					</div>
				</div>
				</div>
		]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/addiction-help/help-for-loved-ones/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Addiction Help for Myself</title>
		<link>https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/addiction-help/help-for-myself/</link>
					<comments>https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/addiction-help/help-for-myself/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ellyn Iacovou]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 09 Apr 2025 14:04:20 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Addiction Help]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/?p=47394</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[If you are looking for addiction treatment for yourself, this guide will help you prepare for the journey ahead. ]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[		<div data-elementor-type="wp-post" data-elementor-id="47394" class="elementor elementor-47394" data-elementor-post-type="post">
				<div class="elementor-element elementor-element-1a0ae29d e-flex e-con-boxed cmsmasters-block-default e-con e-parent" data-id="1a0ae29d" data-element_type="container">
					<div class="e-con-inner">
				<div class="elementor-element elementor-element-69c86bdc cmsmasters-block-default cmsmasters-sticky-default elementor-widget elementor-widget-text-editor" data-id="69c86bdc" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="text-editor.default">
				<div class="elementor-widget-container">
									<h1>Addiction Help for Myself</h1>
<p><strong>When You Know Something Needs to Change But You&#8217;re Not Sure Where to Start.</strong></p>
<p>Reaching out for help with an addiction can feel overwhelming. Maybe you’ve thought about rehab before, or perhaps this is your first time even considering it. Either way, you’re here and that&#8217;s a huge step. </p>
<p>At Abbington House, we support people who are ready to take a step toward recovery, even if they’re not sure exactly what that step should look like. You don’t have to be absolutely certain, but you have to be open to receiving help. </p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:separator --></p>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />
<p><!-- /wp:separator --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading {"level":3} --></p>
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Why People Come to Us</h3>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Most of the people we work with have tried to stop drinking or using before. Some have had periods of sobriety. Others feel stuck in a pattern they can’t explain or escape. For others, an ultimatum from a loved one has pushed them to seek treatment.</p>
<p>You might be here because:</p>
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul class="wp-block-list"><!-- wp:list-item --></ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>You feel like you&#8217;re losing control of your drinking or drug use</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><!-- /wp:list-item --></p>
<p><!-- wp:list-item --></p>
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>You&#8217;re exhausted by the cycle of guilt, secrecy, or shame</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><!-- /wp:list-item --></p>
<p><!-- wp:list-item --></p>
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>You&#8217;re worried about how this is affecting your work, relationships or health</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><!-- /wp:list-item --></p>
<p><!-- wp:list-item --></p>
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>You want to feel like yourself again, but don’t know how.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><!-- /wp:list-item --></p>
<p><!-- /wp:list --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>You’re not alone in this. And you don’t need to have all the answers right now. Our role is to help you make a decision without judgment.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:separator --></p>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />
<p><!-- /wp:separator --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading {"level":3} --></p>
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">How We Can Support You in Recovery</h3>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Abbington House is a trauma-informed rehab in Hertfordshire that offers private, residential treatment for addiction. But more than that, we offer space to share, to reconnect with who you are underneath the struggle.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Our approach includes:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:list --></p>
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul class="wp-block-list"><!-- wp:list-item --></ul>
</li>
</ul>
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>One-to-one therapy</strong> tailored to you</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><!-- /wp:list-item --></p>
<p><!-- wp:list-item --></p>
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Trauma-informed care</strong>, acknowledging your past without defining you by it</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><!-- /wp:list-item --></p>
<p><!-- wp:list-item --></p>
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Group support</strong> that feels safe, grounded, and rooted in human connection</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><!-- /wp:list-item --></p>
<p><!-- wp:list-item --></p>
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Gentle</strong> <strong>daily structure</strong>, routines, and practices that bring calm and clarity</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><!-- /wp:list-item --></p>
<p><!-- wp:list-item --></p>
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>A home-like setting</strong>, with warmth and dignity in every room, and in every meal that we share together.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><!-- /wp:list-item --></p>
<p><!-- /wp:list --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>You may not realise it yet, but a better version of you is waiting.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><a href="/residential-rehab/">See what makes our programme different</a> →</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:separator --></p>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />
<p><!-- /wp:separator --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading {"level":3} --></p>
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">What If I&#8217;m Not Ready?</h3>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>That’s okay.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>We speak to people every day who are still deciding. Some call to discuss their options and others just need reassurance that change is possible.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>We won’t rush you into making a decision and won&#8217;t push you into treatment. We’ll listen, and if you want, we’ll help you explore whether Abbington House feels right for you.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>It all starts with one conversation.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:separator --></p>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />
<p><!-- /wp:separator --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading {"level":3} --></p>
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">What to Expect When You Call</h3>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>We know this isn’t easy, so we’ve made the first step feel as stress-free as possible.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>When you call:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:list {"ordered":true} --></p>
<ol class="wp-block-list">
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ol class="wp-block-list"><!-- wp:list-item --></ol>
</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>You’ll speak to someone kind, respectful, and experienced (often someone who’s been through recovery themselves)<!-- wp:list-item --><!-- /wp:list-item --></li>
<li>We’ll invite you to share &#8211; but only what you’re comfortable with<!-- wp:list-item --><!-- /wp:list-item --></li>
<li>We’ll talk through what you need and what your options are<!-- wp:list-item --><!-- /wp:list-item --></li>
<li>If you’d like to move forward, we’ll walk you through every detail.</li>
</ul>
<p><!-- /wp:list-item --></p>
<p><!-- /wp:list --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>You can call, email or chat with us on Livechat if you feel more comfortable.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><a href="/contact-us/">Contact Abbington House</a> →</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:separator --></p>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />
<p><!-- /wp:separator --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading {"level":3} --></p>
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Real Stories, Real People</h3>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Many of our team members have been through addiction and recovery themselves. We know the courage it takes to ask for help because we’ve been in this very position before. We know what a difference the right support can make.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:html --></p>
<div id="06xfo7he"> </div>
<p><script src="https://www.doctify.com/get-script?widget_container_id=06xfo7he&amp;type=horizontal-widget&amp;tenant=athena-uk&amp;language=en&amp;profileType=practice&amp;layoutType=layoutXL&amp;slugs=abbington-house&amp;background=white"></script></p>
<p><!-- /wp:html --></p>
<p><!-- wp:separator --></p>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity" />
<p><!-- /wp:separator --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading {"level":3} --></p>
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Ready When You Are</h3>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>You don’t need to wait for a rock bottom moment. If you’re questioning your drinking or drug use, or if something is telling you it’s time for change, then that’s enough.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>We&#8217;re here to talk, whenever you’re ready.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p> </p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>								</div>
				</div>
				<div class="elementor-element elementor-element-c802e3e cmsmasters-icon-arrangement-together cmsmasters-block-default cmsmasters-sticky-default elementor-widget elementor-widget-cmsmasters-button" data-id="c802e3e" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="cmsmasters-button.default">
				<div class="elementor-widget-container">
					<div class="elementor-widget-cmsmasters-button__button-container"><div class="elementor-widget-cmsmasters-button__button-container-inner"><a href="tel:01438583222" class="cmsmasters-button-link elementor-widget-cmsmasters-button__button cmsmasters-icon-view-default cmsmasters-icon-shape- cmsmasters-button-size-sm" role="button"><span class="elementor-widget-cmsmasters-button__content-wrapper cmsmasters-align-icon-left"><span class="elementor-widget-cmsmasters-button__icon"><i aria-hidden="true" class="cmsdemo-icon- cms-demo-icon-phone"></i></span><span class="elementor-widget-cmsmasters-button__text">Call Us Now</span></span></a></div></div>				</div>
				</div>
					</div>
				</div>
				</div>
		]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/addiction-help/help-for-myself/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Cost of Private Rehab in the UK</title>
		<link>https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/private-rehab/rehab-costs-uk/</link>
					<comments>https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/private-rehab/rehab-costs-uk/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rob Lloyd]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2025 23:26:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Private Rehab]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/?p=46816</guid>

					<description><![CDATA["How much does rehab cost" is often the first question, but this depends on factors including programme length.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>When someone you love is struggling with addiction or when you’re facing that reality yourself, one of the first questions that often comes to mind is: <strong>how much does private rehab actually cost?</strong> It’s a valid and urgent concern, especially when you&#8217;re trying to balance emotional overwhelm with practical planning. Perhaps the biggest concern of all: can I really afford it?</p>



<p>The short answer to &#8216;how much does rehab cost&#8217; is: it depends. The longer, more helpful answer is that private rehab costs vary based on a number of factors which we will explore in this article. If you are concerned about costs, it’s possible to find high-quality, safe, and compassionate care that doesn’t rely on luxury price tags or hidden extras.</p>



<p>At Abbington House, we believe in <strong>transparent, fixed </strong>prices based on programme length. As part of your treatment costs, food and accommodation are provided on-site at no additional cost. You can learn more about what is included in our fees below.</p>



<p>First, we’ll walk you through the costs of private rehab in the UK, what influences pricing, and how to ensure you’re choosing a service that reflects value and not just expense.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">How Much Does Private Rehab Cost in the UK?</h2>



<p>The average cost of a <strong>28-day private residential programme in the UK</strong> ranges from <strong>£8000 to £12,000</strong>, depending on the location, services, and level of clinical support provided.</p>



<p>Here’s a breakdown of typical pricing across different levels of care:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-table alignfull"><table class="has-fixed-layout"><thead><tr><th>Estimated 28-Day Cost</th><th>What’s Included</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Quasi-Residential: £6,000 – £8000</td><td>Group therapy, shared room, detox support</td></tr><tr><td>Mid-Range: £9,000 – £12,000</td><td>Private room, bi-weekly 1:1 therapy. Group therapy, holistic therapies, family support programme, aftercare</td></tr><tr><td>High End: £12,000 – £30,000+</td><td>Spa-level amenities, private consultants, long-term stays (secondary)</td></tr><tr><td>Detox Only &#8211; £2,500 – £6,000</td><td>24/7 medical monitoring, medication, meals, accommodation (single or shared)</td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p>The <strong><a href="https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/alcohol-rehab/costs/" data-type="page" data-id="48568">cost of alcohol rehab</a></strong> and the cost of <strong>drug rehab</strong> are generally the same. Some treatment clinics may slightly increase fees depending on individual needs.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What Affects the Cost of Private Rehab?</h2>



<p>The cost of private addiction treatment is  tied closely to the <strong>level of safety, specialisation, and support</strong> being offered. Here are the key factors that influence price:</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">1. Type of Programme</h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Detox-only</strong> stays are short-term, focused on physical withdrawal, and may not include therapy or emotional recovery work.</li>



<li><strong>28-day residential programmes</strong> provide structured, therapeutic environments that support both detox and mental health.</li>



<li><strong>Extended programmes</strong> (6–12 weeks) are often recommended for clients with complex trauma, mental health conditions, or relapse history.</li>
</ul>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">2. Medical Support and Supervision</h3>



<p>Medical detox especially for alcohol, benzodiazepines, or opioids, may require 24/7 clinical monitoring. Programmes that include on-site doctors, nurses, or psychiatric input naturally incur higher costs due to staffing, prescription management, and safety protocols. This is particularly important for dual diagnosis clients who need integrated support.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">3. Location and Setting</h3>



<p>Rehabs in central London or high-demand areas tend to be more expensive due to overheads and real estate. Facilities like <strong>Abbington House</strong>, located in the quiet Hertfordshire countryside, offer a private, restorative setting without the premium pricing of city-based centres.</p>



<p>A peaceful setting not only impacts cost but it enhances the recovery environment. Being away from triggers, noise, and chaos often helps clients engage more deeply in their recovery journey.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">4. Staff-to-Client Ratio</h3>



<p>Low-cost programmes often accommodate high volumes of clients with minimal staff, reducing therapeutic contact and increasing risk. At Abbington House, our low client to staff ratio ensure every individual receives the time, attention, and custom support they deserve.</p>



<p>More staff = more availability, more safety, and more personalised care.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">5. What’s Included in the Price of Treatment?</h3>



<p>Many providers advertise attractive “from” prices but once you arrive, therapy, medication, laundry or even meals might be added on separately.</p>



<p>At Abbington House, we operate on a <strong>fully inclusive model</strong>, so the price you’re quoted is the price you pay. Our programme includes:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Full medical assessment and detox if required</li>



<li>Group therapy and bi-weekly one-to-one therapy.</li>



<li>Family therapy and support.</li>



<li>Private accommodation</li>



<li>Daily meals from our nutritional chef</li>



<li>Holistic therapies such as yoga, art, and breathwork</li>



<li>Tailored aftercare planning and ongoing alumni support.</li>
</ul>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">How Does Private Rehab Compare to NHS-Funded Treatment?</h2>



<p>While the <strong>NHS does not operate its own residential rehabs</strong>, local services may sometimes fund placements in external rehab centres. However, these opportunities are limited, subject to tight eligibility criteria, and often require individuals to demonstrate multiple unsuccessful attempts at community-based recovery before being considered.</p>



<p>Most NHS-funded services consist of <strong>outpatient support</strong> delivered through local drug and alcohol teams. These services can be life-saving and are a vital part of the UK’s public health infrastructure but they are also under-resourced, oversubscribed, and not always suitable for individuals in crisis.</p>



<p>Here’s how the care compares:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-table alignwide"><table class="has-fixed-layout"><thead><tr><th>Private <br>Residential Rehab</th><th>NHS-Funded Services</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Admission Within 24–72 hours</td><td>8–16+ weeks wait, or longer</td></tr><tr><td>Safe, residential, distraction-free</td><td>Home-based, vulnerable to triggers</td></tr><tr><td>24/7 clinical monitoring</td><td>Often external or unavailable</td></tr><tr><td>Weekly 1:1 individual therapy and group sessions</td><td>Weekly or biweekly keywork only</td></tr><tr><td>Planned, proactive, and connected</td><td>Limited, varies by region</td></tr><tr><td>Designed around individual needs</td><td>One-size-fits-most</td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<p>Private rehab is not “better” because it’s paid for. It’s more intensive, structured, and immediate. For people with high-risk behaviours, long-term use, or co-occurring mental health conditions, it provides the kind of comprehensive containment and support that community options may not be able to offer.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Can I Afford to Pay for Rehab?</h2>



<p>For many families, the idea of private rehab can feel financially out of reach especially in the middle of crisis. But understanding what you&#8217;re paying for (and what you’re saving by acting early) can help put things into perspective.</p>



<p>Think about what untreated addiction costs over time:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Repeated hospital visits</li>



<li>Lost income due to sick days or job loss</li>



<li>Legal issues</li>



<li>Damage to relationships, housing stability, or mental health</li>
</ul>



<p>Private rehab isn&#8217;t a luxury, it’s an investment<strong> </strong>in long-term wellbeing. Paying for rehab treatment puts you first, in a safe and secure environment. </p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Funding Drug or Alcohol Rehab: Your Options</h2>



<p>If you&#8217;re worried about affordability, you&#8217;re not alone. Many families explore multiple funding options to make rehab possible:</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">1. Family and Friends</h3>



<p>Loved ones are often willing to help either through pooled support, loans, or shared resources. When framed as an investment in someone’s life and future, family support can become a powerful act of commitment.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">2. Employer or Health Insurance (If Available)</h3>



<p>In some cases, private health insurance may cover addiction treatment. Similarly, some employers offer access to Employee Assistance Programmes (EAPs) or temporary funding for crisis care.</p>



<p>Always speak with your employer confidentially especially if your addiction is impacting your work. You may be entitled to protected leave under health legislation.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What’s the Cost of a Programme at Abbington House?</h2>



<p>At Abbington House, we don’t believe in vague “from” pricing or hidden add-ons. Instead, we offer <strong>fixed-cost programmes</strong> based on the length of your stay, with clarity around what’s included from the moment you enquire.</p>



<p>Your quoted rehabilitation cost includes:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>A tailored care plan and optional medical detox</li>



<li>Comfortable accommodation in a peaceful setting</li>



<li>Nutritious meals cooked by our experienced chef</li>



<li>Daily group therapy and regular one-to-one counselling</li>



<li>Medication (if required for detox and stabilisation)</li>



<li>Holistic support such as art therapy, breathwork and mindfulness</li>



<li>Weekly activities including gym sessions and swimming</li>



<li>Family support throughout the programme</li>



<li>Dedicated aftercare planning and optional alumni access</li>
</ul>



<p>If you&#8217;re exploring treatment, the best way to understand pricing is to have a <strong>confidential, honest conversation</strong> with our admissions team. We’ll talk you through your options, what your needs are, and whether we’re the right fit.</p>



<p>Even if you’re not ready to commit we’re here to listen.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Take the First Step</h2>



<p>You don’t have to make every decision right now. But if you’re asking questions about cost, treatment, or what comes next,  it means you’re already moving forward.</p>



<p>Whether you’re struggling with alcohol, substances, or a loved one’s wellbeing, Abbington House is here to help you find a safe, compassionate next step.</p>



<p>We offer:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Transparent fixed-fee pricing</li>



<li>Immediate admissions when needed</li>



<li>A peaceful, private setting in Hertfordshire, only 30 minutes from London</li>



<li>Therapy tailored for trauma, self-regulation and empowerment. </li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Call us today</strong> to learn more or send us a message via the Livechat feature. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/private-rehab/rehab-costs-uk/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>What Is Private Rehab?</title>
		<link>https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/private-rehab/what-is-private-rehab/</link>
					<comments>https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/private-rehab/what-is-private-rehab/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ellyn Iacovou]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 12:25:39 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Private Rehab]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/?p=46631</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Private rehab refers to residential or outpatient addiction treatment programmes that are funded by the individual or their family, rather than the NHS or public services.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>When most people hear the word “rehab,” they imagine sterile hospital corridors or chaotic crisis centres &#8211; but private rehab is something entirely different. It’s not just about detoxing from substances. It’s about recovery on a deeper level: emotional, psychological, and spiritual healing that takes place in a safe, structured, and private environment.</p>



<p>Private rehab refers to <strong><a href="https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/residential-rehab/" data-type="page" data-id="38803">residential</a> or outpatient addiction treatment programmes</strong> that are funded by the individual or their family, rather than the NHS or public services. These centres are typically faster to access, more flexible in their approach, and able to offer <strong>bespoke, trauma-informed care</strong> that aligns with each person’s specific needs. At facilities like Abbington House, private rehab is also a place where dignity, comfort, and discretion are prioritised.</p>



<p>For many people, especially those who have been &#8220;functioning&#8221; with addiction or masking their pain for years, private rehab offers something vital that public systems often can&#8217;t &#8211; <strong>space and time to feel safe again</strong>.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">How Does Private Rehab Work?</h2>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">A Personalised Approach With Immediate Access</h3>



<p>In private rehab, <strong>there are no waiting lists</strong>. Once a person is ready, the <a href="https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/admissions/" data-type="page" data-id="41609">process of admission</a> can often happen within 24–48 hours. Unlike public systems which may prioritise acute crisis cases or offer time-limited care, private facilities can tailor every aspect of treatment to the individual’s background, medical needs, mental health history, and personal circumstances.</p>



<p>Upon admission, clients undergo an in-depth clinical and psychological assessment. This isn’t a tick-box exercise &#8211; it’s the beginning of a deeply personal healing plan. Whether someone needs <strong>medically supervised detox</strong>, therapy for trauma, or support for co-occurring conditions like <strong>ADHD or anxiety</strong>, private rehab builds the plan around them, not the other way around.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">What Makes Private Rehab Different?</h3>



<p>The key differences between <strong>private</strong> and <strong>public (NHS)</strong> rehab services come down to three areas: access, quality of care, and individual focus. Here’s how they compare:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-table"><table class="has-fixed-layout"><thead><tr><th>Private Rehab</th><th>NHS/Public Treatment</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Immediate (24–48 hours) access to treatment.</td><td>Wait times can be weeks to months.</td></tr><tr><td>Flexible, based on client needs</td><td>Often fixed or limited</td></tr><tr><td>Home-like, discreet, high-comfort</td><td>Hospital-style or clinical outpatient settings</td></tr><tr><td>Holistic and trauma-informed</td><td>Standardised community-based care</td></tr><tr><td>1:1 and specialist therapy available</td><td>Primarily group-based sessions</td></tr><tr><td>Aftercare Included and tailored</td><td>Additional support varies. Often referral-based and limited</td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<p>For someone who has tried to get help before and fallen through the cracks, private rehab offers a genuine turning point and higher standards of care.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Why People Choose Private Rehab Over Public Services</h2>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">When You’ve Tried Everything Else</h3>



<p>Some people enter private rehab after trying NHS support or local outpatient services, only to find that the <strong>one-size-fits-all</strong> approach doesn’t work for them. Others may have never reached out before, too fearful of being stigmatised or too busy caring for others to prioritise themselves.</p>



<p>Private rehab appeals to those who:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Want to avoid NHS waiting times</li>



<li>Need discretion due to career or family reputation</li>



<li>Live with <strong>co-occurring mental health conditions</strong> like trauma, depression, or PTSD</li>



<li>Need <strong>a safe environment</strong> away from home triggers or unsafe relationships</li>



<li>Have been to rehab before and want a deeper, more sustainable recovery.</li>
</ul>



<p>It’s not about “buying recovery.” It’s about creating the right conditions for it to take root.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">The Role of Privacy and Emotional Safety</h3>



<p>For many high-functioning individuals—professionals, caregivers, people of faith, or those in the public eye &#8211; <strong>privacy isn’t a luxury, it’s a necessity</strong>. Addiction often carries a deep layer of shame, and without a space that feels emotionally safe, people are unlikely to fully open up, let alone begin healing.</p>



<p>Private rehab offers:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Confidential admissions and discreet location</strong></li>



<li><strong>Private rooms</strong> or low-occupancy accommodations</li>



<li>The freedom to share without fear of exposure</li>



<li>Greater emotional bandwidth from staff.</li>
</ul>



<p>This level of care fosters not just abstinence, but a chance for real, personal development. </p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p><em>Next, we’ll explore the core benefits of choosing a private rehab programme &#8211; including personalised therapy, trauma support, and long-term recovery planning.</em></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">The Benefits of Choosing Private Rehab</h2>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Personalised Care That Goes Beyond the Basics</h3>



<p>Perhaps the most defining feature of private rehab is the degree to which <strong>treatment is tailored to the individual</strong>. Instead of rigid protocols or generalised group work, private rehab begins with a deep, human assessment of each person’s needs—mental, emotional, spiritual, and physical.</p>



<p>At centres like Abbington House, this process involves:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>A full clinical and psychiatric evaluation</li>



<li>Exploration of co-occurring conditions (e.g., ADHD, PTSD, anxiety)</li>



<li>Consideration of trauma history, emotional regulation, and neurodivergence</li>



<li>Preferences and comfort levels with therapy styles and communication</li>
</ul>



<p>This enables the care team to develop a <strong>genuinely bespoke treatment plan</strong>—one that evolves in real time. If you’re struggling to connect in group therapy, we pivot. If your trauma requires gentle, body-first approaches, we adapt. That level of responsiveness is rare in the public sector, where resources are often stretched thin.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">A Safe, Comfortable Environment That Supports Recovery</h3>



<p>Environment matters—especially when recovering from something as all-encompassing as addiction. Private rehab provides <strong>a setting that feels human, not clinical</strong>, allowing individuals to rest, reset, and begin emotional repair.</p>



<p>Features of this environment often include:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Peaceful residential homes with gardens and private rooms</li>



<li>Communal spaces for social healing—without overcrowding</li>



<li>Access to nature, light, movement, and privacy</li>



<li>Chefs preparing nourishing, stabilising meals for body and mind</li>
</ul>



<p>This isn&#8217;t about luxury—it’s about <strong>creating psychological safety</strong>. When the body feels safe, the nervous system can start to regulate. And when that happens, the real work of recovery begins.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Faster Access, Longer Support</h3>



<p>One of the most immediate advantages of private rehab is <strong>how quickly treatment can begin</strong>. In the NHS, referral systems, eligibility checks, and waiting lists often cause delays of weeks or months. In private settings, people are often admitted within a few days—and sometimes within 24 hours of enquiry.</p>



<p>Equally important is what happens afterward. Unlike public services that may provide only minimal follow-up, <strong>private rehab includes comprehensive aftercare</strong>, such as:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Ongoing therapy referrals and weekly check-ins</li>



<li>Access to alumni networks or online support groups</li>



<li>Tailored relapse prevention plans</li>



<li>Family education sessions and reintegration coaching</li>
</ul>



<p>Because rehab should be the start of something, not the end.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What Treatments Are Offered in Private Rehab?</h2>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Medically Assisted Detox: Safe, Supervised, and Supported</h3>



<p>For many clients, the first stage of treatment is <a href="https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/residential-rehab/medically-supervised-detox/" data-type="residential-rehab" data-id="41719">detox</a> &#8211; the process of physically clearing drugs or alcohol from the body. In private rehab, this is conducted under <strong>medical supervision</strong>, with a focus on safety, comfort, and dignity.</p>



<p>The process often includes:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>24/7 monitoring by clinical staff</li>



<li>Use of prescribed medications to ease withdrawal symptoms</li>



<li>Nutritional and hydration support</li>



<li>Emotional reassurance and trauma-sensitive care</li>
</ul>



<p>Detox is one of the most vulnerable stages of recovery, and how it’s handled sets the tone for the entire rehab experience.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Residential Rehab: Structure and Depth</h3>



<p>After detox, clients typically enter the <strong>rehabilitation phase of treatment</strong>, lasting anywhere from two to twelve weeks depending on individual needs. This time is spent addressing not just the addiction itself, but the <strong>underlying patterns, pain, and protective mechanisms</strong> that fuel it.</p>



<p>Typical elements of a residential programme include:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Regular 1:1 therapy including <a href="https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/residential-rehab/trauma-therapies/" data-type="residential-rehab" data-id="41711">trauma therapy</a> with a dedicated counsellor</li>



<li>Group therapy and the <a href="https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/residential-rehab/12-step-programme/" data-type="residential-rehab" data-id="41715">12-steps</a>, process work, and peer support</li>



<li>Psychoeducation about addiction, trauma, and emotional regulation</li>



<li><a href="https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/residential-rehab/holistic-healing/" data-type="residential-rehab" data-id="41723">Holistic therapies</a> (e.g., Mindfulness, yoga, sound therapy or somatic grounding.)</li>
</ul>



<p>Each day follows a structured but balanced routine &#8211; enough to support accountability, but flexible enough to respect individual needs.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Outpatient Support and Aftercare</h3>



<p>Once the residential stay ends, many private rehabs offer <strong>step-down support</strong> that bridges the gap between treatment and daily life. This may include outpatient counselling, virtual check-ins, family therapy sessions, or peer support groups.</p>



<p>The best private rehabs (including Abbington House) <strong>build the exit strategy early on in the rehab journey</strong>, ensuring:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>You leave with a complete <a href="https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/residential-rehab/aftercare-programme/" data-type="residential-rehab" data-id="41735">aftercare plan</a></li>



<li>You stay connected to the team if desired</li>



<li>You know exactly where to go if challenges arise later.</li>
</ul>



<p>Leaving rehab should feel like moving forward, but part of that process needs to ensure you have a safety net when things feel difficult, this is especially important in the early stages of recovery.  </p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Who Is Private Rehab For?</h2>



<p>Many people assume that addiction has a “look” &#8211; chaos, dysfunction, or visible collapse. But the truth is, some of the most deeply struggling individuals are also the ones who <strong>seem fine on the surface</strong>.</p>



<p>Private rehab offers safety and discretion for:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>CEOs, teachers, healthcare workers, lawyers, medical professionals</li>



<li>Parents balancing home life with hidden drinking</li>



<li>People in faith communities or public roles</li>



<li>Caregivers, therapists, or support workers</li>



<li>Those with mental health needs in addition to substance abuse issues</li>
</ul>



<p>At Abbington House, we meet people every day from all walks of life. </p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">People With Trauma or Neurodivergence</h3>



<p>Public rehab often struggles to support people with <strong>complex emotional needs</strong>. Private care, on the other hand, recognises that addiction is rarely just about substances.</p>



<p>We specialise in helping people with:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Unprocessed trauma or CPTSD</strong></li>



<li><strong>ADHD and masking</strong></li>



<li><strong>Autism with sensory or emotional sensitivities</strong></li>



<li><strong>Anxiety, OCD, or eating distress</strong></li>
</ul>



<p>Our approach is not to confront or shame, but to gently support regulation, connection, and internal safety.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">First-Timers and Repeat Visitors</h3>



<p>Some people come to private rehab as their first attempt at recovery. Others come after <strong>multiple rehab experiences</strong>. </p>



<p>Private rehab can succeed where others haven’t because it:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Gives time, not pressure</li>



<li>Offers individual support over one-size-fits-all approaches</li>



<li>Treats you like a person &#8211; not a patient.</li>
</ul>



<p>Wherever you’re starting from, private care meets you there.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p><em>Next, we’ll explore the costs of private rehab in the UK &#8211; and what’s actually included in the investment you make.</em></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Paying for Treatment</h2>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Breaking Down the Investment</h3>



<p>When considering private rehab, cost is often the first question &#8211; and for good reason. While there’s no denying that private treatment carries a financial investment, it’s important to understand what you’re really paying for: <strong>time, safety, focus, and access to specialist care</strong> that public services often cannot provide.</p>



<p>In the UK, the cost of private rehab varies significantly depending on:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>The <strong>length of stay</strong> (e.g., 7 days vs 28+ days)</li>



<li>The <strong>type of programme</strong> (detox only, full residential, quasi-residential, outpatient)</li>



<li>The <strong>centre’s location, facilities, and clinical credentials</strong></li>



<li>Whether <strong>medical detox is required</strong></li>



<li>Whether a room is <strong>private or shared</strong></li>
</ul>



<p>While this may feel out of reach for some, many centres offer <strong>flexible programme lengths</strong> or work with <strong>health insurance providers</strong>. Some employers, especially within corporate or medical sectors, may also have <strong>EAP (Employee Assistance Programmes)</strong> that cover partial or full costs of private addiction treatment.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">What’s Included in the Cost?</h3>



<p>One of the benefits of private rehab is transparency &#8211; you should know what you’re getting upfront. While inclusions may vary between facilities, most high-quality private rehabs offer:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>24/7 accommodation and support</strong></li>



<li><strong>Full medical assessments</strong></li>



<li><strong>Medically supervised detox (if needed)</strong></li>



<li><strong>Individual and group therapy sessions</strong></li>



<li><strong>Complementary therapies (e.g., yoga, mindfulness, nutrition)</strong></li>



<li><strong>Family therapy or involvement (if appropriate)</strong></li>



<li><strong>Aftercare planning and support</strong></li>
</ul>



<p>There should be <strong>no hidden charges</strong> for medication, meals, or basic amenities. The goal is to remove all unnecessary stressors, allowing clients to focus solely on their recovery journey. Most private treatment centres do not put prices on their website, but you should be able to call them and find out. </p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Thinking Beyond the Price Tag</h3>



<p>When assessing cost, it’s helpful to consider the <strong>long-term emotional, physical, and financial toll</strong> of untreated addiction:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Lost income or employment due to substance-related issues</li>



<li>Ongoing mental health crises and repeat GP or A&amp;E visits</li>



<li>Legal problems or relationship breakdowns</li>



<li>Physical health deterioration (e.g., liver damage, heart issues)</li>
</ul>



<p>Private rehab, in this sense, can be seen not just as a cost &#8211; but as a <strong>protective investment</strong> into future wellbeing, stability, and longevity. </p>



<p>You can view our guide to the <a href="https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/private-rehab/rehab-costs-uk/" data-type="post" data-id="46816">cost of rehab in the UK here</a>, which provides a more detailed breakdown of the varying costs.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">How to Choose the Right Private Rehab for You</h2>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Questions to Ask Before Committing</h3>



<p>Choosing a rehab centre is a deeply personal decision. It’s not just about facilities or cost &#8211; it’s about <strong>fit, values, and the emotional safety you feel from the first phone call</strong>.</p>



<p>Before choosing, consider asking:</p>



<ol class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>What’s your approach to trauma and co-occurring mental health conditions?</strong></li>



<li><strong>Are your therapists fully accredited (e.g., BACP, UKCP)?</strong></li>



<li><strong>What is the daily structure like &#8211; how much 1:1 support is available?</strong></li>



<li><strong>How do you handle relapse or resistance during treatment?</strong></li>



<li><strong>Can family members be involved in any part of the process?</strong></li>



<li><strong>What kind of aftercare is offered once I leave?</strong></li>



<li><strong>Does the programme offer flexibility?</strong></li>
</ol>



<p>These are important questions to ask before committed to treatment. The more personalised the care, the better. </p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Accreditation and Specialisms Matter</h3>



<p>Not all rehab centres are created equal. Reputable private rehabs in the UK should be registered with the <strong>Care Quality Commission (CQC)</strong> and employ <strong>trained, experienced clinicians</strong> across therapy, nursing, and psychiatric care.</p>



<p>Look for centres that offer:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Trauma-informed frameworks</strong> (e.g., EMDR, somatic experiencing)</li>



<li>Experience supporting <strong>neurodivergent individuals</strong></li>



<li><strong>Dual-diagnosis treatment</strong> (for addiction + mental health)</li>



<li>A team with multidisciplinary oversight &#8211; not just addiction counsellors</li>
</ul>



<p>You deserve care that understands <em>all</em> of you &#8211; not just the part that drinks or uses. Recovery goes beyond the treatment of addiction. A good private rehab in the UK should cater for the whole individual. </p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Location and Accessibility</h3>



<p>Some people want to be close to home so that family can visit or participate in therapy. Others prefer to <strong>create physical distance from familiar triggers</strong>, opting for more secluded centres where healing can take root without distraction.</p>



<p>Abbington House, for example, is tucked away in the Hertfordshire countryside &#8211; but is still easily accessible from London and surrounding areas like Watford, Hemel Hempstead, and St Albans. This balance of proximity and privacy makes it ideal for those needing discretion without total isolation. </p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Private Rehab at Abbington House: A Human-First Approach</h2>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">A Rehab That Feels Like Home &#8211; Because It Is One</h3>



<p>At Abbington House, we’ve reimagined rehab as a space where <strong>safety, respect, and humanity come first</strong>. We don’t believe in stripping away autonomy, routines, or identity. We believe in building people up with the tools they need to live well again.</p>



<p>Our team specialises in working with:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Individuals with <strong>sensory sensitivities</strong></li>



<li>Clients who have experienced <strong>trauma, grief, or burnout</strong></li>



<li>Professionals and carers who’ve been holding it together for too long</li>



<li>People who’ve tried other rehabs and felt misunderstood.</li>
</ul>



<p>We’re not just clinical. We’re <strong>trauma-informed, person-centred, and emotionally fluent</strong>. Our therapists are accredited. Our staff are warm, experienced, and attuned. Our chef cooks with purpose. Our alumni come back &#8211; not because they have to, but because they want to stay connected.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">What to Expect From Day One</h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>A warm welcome with no judgment</li>



<li>A quiet, calming bedroom that feels like your own space</li>



<li>A full assessment with a lead clinician who listens to you—not a clipboard</li>



<li>A flexible, evolving plan that meets you where you are</li>



<li>Nourishing meals, soft routines, time to rest, and real emotional work</li>
</ul>



<p>Call the Abbington House team today to learn more about private rehab and treatment costs.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Learn more about <a href="https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/alcohol-rehab/" data-type="page" data-id="41629">alcohol rehab</a> at Abbington House</li>



<li>Learn more about <a href="https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/drug-rehab/" data-type="page" data-id="45341">drug rehab</a> at Abbington House</li>
</ul>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/private-rehab/what-is-private-rehab/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Why Reddit Isn’t the Best Place to Get Addiction Treatment Advice</title>
		<link>https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/rehab-advice/reddit-addiction-advice/</link>
					<comments>https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/rehab-advice/reddit-addiction-advice/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rob Lloyd]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 19:40:28 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Rehab Advice]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/?p=46408</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Reddit is not clinical. It’s not moderated by therapists, addiction medicine specialists, or safeguarding professionals. And most importantly, it doesn’t know you.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[		<div data-elementor-type="wp-post" data-elementor-id="46408" class="elementor elementor-46408" data-elementor-post-type="post">
				<div class="elementor-element elementor-element-30155cbb e-flex e-con-boxed cmsmasters-block-default e-con e-parent" data-id="30155cbb" data-element_type="container">
					<div class="e-con-inner">
				<div class="elementor-element elementor-element-49d3d05f cmsmasters-block-default cmsmasters-sticky-default elementor-widget elementor-widget-text-editor" data-id="49d3d05f" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="text-editor.default">
				<div class="elementor-widget-container">
									<p></p>
<p>I’ve spent nearly eight years working in the addiction treatment space &#8211; writing, creating, learning and helping clinics communicate better with the people they serve. While I’ve never personally had a substance issue that needed treatment, I have ADHD, and I’ve dealt with enough compulsive behaviours to understand how easy it is to fall into a cycle that feels impossible to break.</p>
<p></p>
<p>One thing I’ve seen increasingly over the last few years, especially among younger people and neurodivergent communities, is a growing reliance on Reddit for addiction advice. I get it. Reddit feels real, unfiltered and raw. It’s where people speak the truth others are too scared to say out loud &#8211; but I’ve also seen the harm it causes. Not because people are bad but because the platform is built to reward emotion over evidence&nbsp;and upvotes over nuance.</p>
<p></p>
<p>So if you&#8217;re scrolling r/addiction, r/stopdrinking, or similar subs looking for guidance, please keep reading. This isn’t a takedown of Reddit; it’s a conversation about where it fits <em>and</em> where it fails in the world of recovery.</p>
<p></p>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity">
<p></p>
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Reddit Can Be a Lifeline, But It&#8217;s Not a Treatment Plan</h2>
<p></p>
<p>Let me be clear: I’ve read incredible threads on Reddit. Moments of compassion, honesty, and mutual support that would rival any therapy room. There’s power in peer communities, and sometimes hearing “me too” from a stranger at 2am can feel life-saving (2am is when my brain is most active).</p>
<p></p>
<p>But here’s where it gets tricky.</p>
<p></p>
<p>Reddit is not clinical. It’s not moderated by therapists, addiction medicine specialists, or safeguarding professionals. And most importantly, it doesn’t know <em>you</em>. It doesn’t know your mental health history, your trauma background, your medication interactions, or how many units you’ve been drinking per day. Reddit doesn’t know whether you’re in withdrawal or burnout. It can’t tell if your drinking is masking PTSD, or if your “just one more night” will lead to seizures.</p>
<p></p>
<p>Yet advice is thrown around like truth, often from people with no qualifications, just a strong opinion and a few thousand karma points.</p>
<p></p>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity">
<p></p>
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">The Misinformation Loop: When the Reddit Echo Chambers Take Over</h2>
<p></p>
<p>One of the most common patterns I see on Reddit is what I call the echo loop. It looks like this:</p>
<p></p>
<ol class="wp-block-list"><p></p>
<li>Someone posts a vulnerable question: “Should I detox cold turkey?”</li>
<p></p>
<li>A few commenters reply, “I did it and was fine.”</li>
<p></p>
<li>Others add, “Rehabs just want your money anyway.”</li>
<p></p>
<li>The post gets upvoted. The risky advice gets reinforced.</li>
<p></p>
</ol>
<p></p>
<p>And just like that, the really bad advice becomes the top answer.</p>
<p></p>
<p>This isn’t a Reddit-specific problem; it’s a platform design problem. On Reddit, the content that rises is content that feels right, not content that is right. That means emotional stories get more traction than evidence-based responses. Posts with nuance like “it depends on your medical history, speak to a GP” &#8211; get buried.</p>
<p></p>
<p>In addiction, that’s dangerous.</p>
<p></p>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity">
<p></p>
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Reddit Doesn’t Screen for Trauma, ADHD or Mental Health Risks</h2>
<p></p>
<p>One of the most harmful myths I see is the idea that addiction is just about willpower. That you can “see it through” if you want it badly enough. But having worked with hundreds of people in recovery, I know this is dangerously simplistic.</p>
<p></p>
<p>Many people who struggle with alcohol or drug use have c<strong>o-occurring conditions</strong>:</p>
<p></p>
<ul class="wp-block-list"><p></p>
<li>ADHD</li>
<p></p>
<li>Complex PTSD</li>
<p></p>
<li>Depression and anxiety</li>
<p></p>
<li>Autism spectrum traits</li>
<p></p>
<li>Grief, neglect, abuse, or childhood trauma</li>
<p></p>
</ul>
<p></p>
<p>When Reddit users offer advice without understanding these layers, they unintentionally cause harm. Telling someone to &#8220;just quit&#8221; without acknowledging their nervous system dysregulation is like telling a drowning person to &#8220;just swim&#8221;.</p>
<p></p>
<p>Trauma needs context. ADHD needs a flexible structure. Autism needs sensitivity. Addiction needs care and understanding &#8211; not upvotes.</p>
<p></p>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity">
<p></p>
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Real Lives, Real Consequences</h2>
<p></p>
<p>In my line of work, I’ve heard stories I’ll never forget. But some of the &#8220;advice&#8221; I have personally witnessed on Reddit is terrifying</p>
<p></p>
<p>Like the teenager who posted on r/opiates asking how to taper using someone else’s leftover meds.</p>
<p></p>
<p>Or the woman who was told that 12 Step was “a cult&#8221;.</p>
<p></p>
<p>Or perhaps the worst advice I have ever seen on Reddit: &#8220;You only need to worry about withdrawal symptoms if you&#8217;re drinking tons of spirits every day&#8221;.</p>
<p></p>
<p>These are not fringe cases. This is what happens when the loudest voice wins, and context is left out of the equation.</p>
<p></p>
<p>Not to mention that Reddit advice can be country-specific. Doctors in the US may charge &#8220;huge sums of money&#8221; for detox medication, but that isn&#8217;t the case here in the UK.</p>
<p></p>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity">
<p></p>
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">The Bias Against Professional Help</h2>
<p></p>
<p>One thing that surprises many people is how much anti-treatment, anti-medical rhetoric exists on Reddit. This isn&#8217;t just specific to addiction or recovery, but I see it everywhere, from diet recommendations to herbal remedies.</p>
<p></p>
<ul class="wp-block-list"><p></p>
<li>“Rehab is just a money-making scam”</li>
<p></p>
<li>“Therapists make money by keeping you stuck”</li>
<p></p>
<li>“AA brainwashes you&#8221;.</li>
<p></p>
</ul>
<p></p>
<p>Now, don’t get me wrong. Criticism of the addiction treatment industry, or any industry, is perfectly valid. I’ve worked in this space long enough to know that recovery is a difficult journey for many people. There are bad actors, overpriced services, and outdated methods. But the solution isn’t throwing the whole system out. It’s improving it, expanding access, and increasing transparency.</p>
<p></p>
<p>Unfortunately, many Reddit threads skip that part. They move from personal frustration to broad generalisations. And for someone in a fragile state, scared, ashamed and confused &#8211; that can be enough to push them away from getting real help.</p>
<p></p>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity">
<p></p>
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">I Loved Reddit Until It Made Me Anxious</h2>
<p></p>
<p>This part is personal. As someone with ADHD, Reddit felt like a perfect fit: fast, unpredictable, full of novelty. But that constant flood of opinions? The never-ending scroll of “this worked for me” vs “you’re doing it wrong” became overwhelming.</p>
<p></p>
<p>I started noticing how often I’d leave Reddit feeling more anxious than when I logged on. Instead of clarity, I had information fatigue. Instead of guidance, I had ten contradicting opinions and no idea which one to trust.</p>
<p></p>
<p>For someone seeking support with something as serious as addiction, that overwhelm can become paralysis. And paralysis, in recovery, is incredibly risky.</p>
<p></p>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity">
<p></p>
<h2>How to Spot Harmful Advice on Reddit</h2>
<p></p>
<p>Not all Reddit advice is dangerous &#8211; but the lines get blurry when you&#8217;re desperate for clarity. In the early stages of change, you’re vulnerable, your nervous system is overloaded and your inner critic is screaming. And Reddit? Reddit is loud.</p>
<p></p>
<p>Here are some red flags I’ve learned to spot both as someone with ADHD and as someone working in addiction recovery spaces:</p>
<p></p>
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">1. <strong>Absolute Statements</strong></h3>
<p></p>
<p>Advice that starts with “You should always…” or “never trust…” lacks nuance. Recovery is <em>deeply</em> individual. What works for one person may harm another. Be wary of any advice that feels binary or overly confident.</p>
<p>Of course, context is important here. If the recommendation is &#8220;you should always speak to a medical professional before attempting a benzodiazepine detox&#8221;, that is really good advice.&nbsp;</p>
<p></p>
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">2. <strong>Anecdotes Masquerading as Evidence</strong></h3>
<p></p>
<p>Someone saying, “I quit after 10 years cold turkey, and I’m fine,” isn’t data. It’s a personal story. Powerful, yes &#8211; but not a blueprint. Especially when you&#8217;re dealing with medical risk, trauma, or co-occurring conditions.</p>
<p></p>
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">3. <strong>Anti-Treatment Sentiment</strong></h3>
<p></p>
<p>Criticism of systems is healthy. But if someone dismisses <em>all</em> rehab, therapy, medication, or support groups based on one experience—or none—that&#8217;s not guidance. That’s projection.</p>
<p></p>
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">4. <strong>Dismissive or Shaming Comments</strong></h3>
<p></p>
<p>Recovery requires self-compassion. Any post or comment that shames you for struggling, mocks your attempts, or suggests you&#8217;re “not trying hard enough” is toxic, whether it has 2 upvotes or 2,000.</p>
<p></p>
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">5. <strong>Algorithmic Echoes</strong></h3>
<p></p>
<p>Posts with thousands of upvotes might <em>feel</em> more trustworthy. But Reddit rewards what’s popular, not what’s safe. Don’t confuse karma with credibility.</p>
<p></p>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity">
<p></p>
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Safer Alternatives to Reddit for Addiction Support</h2>
<p></p>
<p>Let’s be honest: Google can feel overwhelming. And Reddit is familiar, accessible, even comforting. But there are better places to find help.</p>
<p></p>
<p>Here’s where I signpost people instead:</p>
<p></p>
<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>1. NHS and Local Free Services (UK)</strong></h3>
<p></p>
<ul class="wp-block-list"><p></p>
<li><a href="https://www.nhs.uk/live-well/alcohol-support/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">NHS Alcohol Support</a></li>
<p></p>
<li><a href="https://www.changegrowlive.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Change Grow Live</a></li>
<p></p>
<li><a href="https://www.turning-point.co.uk/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Turning Point</a></li>
<p></p>
</ul>
<p></p>
<p>These are free, confidential, and connected to wider health support systems.</p>
<p></p>
<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>2. Residential Rehab</strong></h3>
<p></p>
<p>For people with high-risk alcohol or drug use, trauma history, or repeated relapses, residential rehab can be an important stepping stone in the recovery journey. I have been fortunate to work with some of the best in the UK and Abbington House is no exception.</p>
<p></p>
<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>3. Peer Support With Clinical Anchoring</strong></h3>
<p></p>
<ul class="wp-block-list"><p></p>
<li><a href="https://www.alcoholics-anonymous.org.uk/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">AA</a> and <a href="https://ukna.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">NA</a></li>
<p></p>
<li><a href="https://smartrecovery.org.uk/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">SMART Recovery</a></li>
<p></p>
</ul>
<p></p>
<p>Regardless of where you are in your journey, meetings should always be a key component of recovery. I recommend that you <a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC2746426/#:~:text=In%20a%20longitudinal%20study%20of,attendance%20had%20lower%20rates%20of" data-type="link" data-id="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC2746426/#:~:text=In%20a%20longitudinal%20study%20of,attendance%20had%20lower%20rates%20of" target="_blank" rel="noopener">take a look at this study</a> if you have any doubts.</p>
<p></p>
<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>4. Therapy</strong></h3>
<p></p>
<p>Trauma-aware therapy has helped me in many ways over the years. Look for someone experienced in:</p>
<p></p>
<ul class="wp-block-list"><p></p>
<li>Addiction and compulsive behaviours</li>
<p></p>
<li>ADHD or autism (if applicable)</li>
<p></p>
<li>Complex trauma (C-PTSD)</li>
<p></p>
<li>Emotional regulation and nervous system work.</li>
<p></p>
</ul>
<p></p>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity">
<p></p>
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">What to Do If You’ve Already Been Misled by Reddit Advice</h2>
<p></p>
<p>If you&#8217;ve followed Reddit advice that made things worse, I want you to hear this loud and clear:</p>
<p></p>
<p><strong>It’s not your fault.</strong></p>
<p></p>
<p>Here’s how to reset:</p>
<p></p>
<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>1. Get a Real Person Involved</strong></h3>
<p></p>
<p>Whether it’s a GP, therapist, our team here at Abbington House, or loved ones &#8211; bring someone offline into your process. Algorithms don’t know your history.</p>
<p></p>
<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>2. Review What You Need</strong></h3>
<p></p>
<ul class="wp-block-list"><p></p>
<li>Do you need medical detox?</li>
<p></p>
<li>Do you need trauma support?</li>
<p></p>
<li>Do you need clarity, structure, or just a place to feel safe?</li>
<p></p>
</ul>
<p></p>
<p>If you are unsure about some of these questions, our team here at Abbington can help you make an informed decision.</p>
<p></p>
<h3 class="wp-block-heading"><strong>3. Give Yourself Grace</strong></h3>
<p></p>
<p>You don’t need to prove anything. Recovery isn’t a race, and it certainly isn’t a Reddit karma game. It’s a deeply human, deeply nonlinear process.</p>
<p></p>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity">
<p></p>
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Why I Wrote This</h2>
<p></p>
<p>I didn’t write this to bash Reddit. I’ll never shame anyone for seeking help <em>anywhere</em> they feel safe enough to ask for it.</p>
<p></p>
<p>But as someone who has spent years working in this industry, I know that a one-size-fits-all approach to recovery doesn&#8217;t work. There are no absolutes or certainties.</p>
<p></p>
<p>Because the truth is:</p>
<p></p>
<ul class="wp-block-list"><p></p>
<li>Recovery is hard enough without misinformation</li>
<p></p>
<li>You deserve real support</li>
<p></p>
<li>Help should empower you, not confuse, shame, or mislead you</li>
<p></p>
<li>You’re allowed to be curious, cautious and critical all at the same time.</li>
<p></p>
</ul>
<p></p>
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity">
<p></p>								</div>
				</div>
					</div>
				</div>
		<div class="elementor-element elementor-element-ab8495e e-flex e-con-boxed cmsmasters-block-default e-con e-parent" data-id="ab8495e" data-element_type="container">
					<div class="e-con-inner">
					</div>
				</div>
				</div>
		]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://abbingtonhouse.co.uk/rehab-advice/reddit-addiction-advice/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
